<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The redemption of the seed of God at hand declaring the return of the True Church out of the wilderness into her former state of glory / [by] Richard Moore.</title>
            <author>Moore, Richard, 1619-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51246</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11766818</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11766818</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51246)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1489:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The redemption of the seed of God at hand declaring the return of the True Church out of the wilderness into her former state of glory / [by] Richard Moore.</title>
                  <author>Moore, Richard, 1619-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>168 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church --  Apostolicity.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48769:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48769:1"/>
            <p>THE REDEMPTION OF THE Seed of God At Hand.</p>
            <p>Declaring the Return of the True Church out of the Wilderneſs into her former State of GLORY.</p>
            <p>RICHARD MOORE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord, Keep ye Judgment and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e; for my Salvation is near to come, and my Righteouſneſs to be revealed,</hi> Iſa. 56.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb facs="tcp:48769:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48769:2"/>
            <head>A TESTIMONY Concerning <hi>RICHARD MOOR.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Author of this Book being a faithful Servant of the Lord, and zealous for the Truth, who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured and travailed in the Work of the Miniſtry, both in <hi>England</hi> and beyond Sea, and was in <hi>Barbadoes</hi> when he wrote this little Book, which was ſome Years ſince; and becauſe the Preſs hath been fully ſupplyed with other Things, there was not an Oportunity to print it; but knowing it was his great Deſire it ſhould be publiſhed, and having now a fit Oportunity, I was willing to anſwer what his Mind then was:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48769:3"/>
He came to <hi>London</hi> to viſit Friends in the 11th Moneth, and there fell ſick, and on the 13th Day of the ſame Moneth he dyed in Peace; and thus much is ſignified concerning him by one who truly loved him for the Truth's ſake.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. H.</signed>
               <dateline>London <date>
                     <hi>the 14th of the 9th Mon</hi> 1676.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48769:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHoever thou art that readeſt this enſuing Treatiſe, if thou findeſt any Thing in it which doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſtrange unto thee in the reading thereof, be not troubled thereat, but ſtand ſtill in the Coolneſs of thy Spirit, and turn in to the Meaſure of the Light of God, which ſhineth forth clearly in thy own Conſcience, and there thou wilt ſee it openly made manifeſt unto thee; but if thou readeſt it in the Power of thy own Will, and therein ſtandeſt expecting to receive Benefit thereby, thou wilt find nothing but Deadneſs and barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for the Appearance of God and his Eternal Truth hath at all Times and Seaſons been contrary to Man's VVill; for it is now as it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in the Days of Old,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48769:4"/>
it comes not by the VVill of Man, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men ſpeak as they are moved by the Spirit of God; and as it was in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages, ſo it is now in this our Day, for he that departeth from Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity maketh him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf a Prey unto this Generation of Evil-doers, who ſet themſelves in Perverſeneſs againſt the Lord, and have hardened their Hearts, and ſtiffned their Necks againſt the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Lord, and of his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Truth; and he is come to be a Croſs to the VVill of all Fleſh; for if the Things of God came according to the will of Man, then the VVorld would receive them; but ſeeing it croſſeth Man's VVill, therefore the VVorld hates it, and calls it Fooliſhneſs and Madneſs, and cryes out, that them that are given up to follow it are Deceivers, and are deluded and bewitched.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48769:4"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> THe Return of the True Church out of the Barren Wilderneſs into her former State and Glory.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Deſtruction of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Myſtery of Iniquity, and the Mother of Harlots, and the Abominations of the whole Earth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> A Revelation of the Man of Sin and Death, wherein he is ſeparated from the Man of Righteouſneſs and Life, which two Men are of two ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Births, which Births proceed from the two Seeds, which two Seeds are herein manifeſted and declared, the one to be the Seed of God, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48769:5"/>
the other the Seed of the Serpent, whoſe Head is now to be bruiſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> A Word of Love unto the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Sion;</hi> and a Hand held forth unto them who are yet in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>'s Captivity, and to them who are yet in the Deſert Wilderneſs.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48769:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>A True Manifeſtation of the Church's Return out of the Barren VVilderneſs, where She hath remained ſince the Dayes of the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>which Church is the true Spouſe, the Lamb's VViſe.</hi> Alſo <hi>the Speedy Downfal of</hi> Babylon <hi>the</hi> Mother <hi>of</hi> Harlots, <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOW is the appointed Time come, wherein the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the God of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> is riſen and ariſing to manifeſt himſelf unto his People, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48769:6"/>
to make himſelf known to thoſe that have long waited for this the Day of his Appearance, unto whom the Son of his Righteouſneſs is ariſing with healing in his Wings; and now is the great Jehov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h appearing in his Dread and in his Power, to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of his Covenant unto <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and to his Seed forever, and he is now gathering his <hi>Elect</hi> from the four Quarters of the Earth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the <hi>Seed of</hi> Jacob out of their Captivity, and the <hi>Outcaſt of</hi> Iſrael from under their Yoak of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
               <p>Therefore prepare thee to meet thy God, O <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for behold he is come and coming <hi>in Ten Thouſand of his Saints,</hi> and who may abide the Day of his Appearance? for the Eyes of the Lord God are upon the ſinful Kingdom, and he will deſtroy it from off the Face of the Earth, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that he will not utterly deſtroy the Houſe of <hi>Jacob;</hi> for behold he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48769:6"/>
ſitteth upon a white Throne, before whoſe Face the Heavens and alſo the Earth ſhall fly away, and their Place ſhall be no more found at all, his Eyes are as a Flame of Fire, and on his Head are many Crowns, and he hath a Name written that no man knows but himſelf, &amp; is clothed with a Veſture dipped in Blood, and his Name is called <hi>The word of God,</hi> and out of his Mouth goeth a ſharp Sword, wherewith he doth ſmite the Nations, and he treadeth the Wine-preſs of the Fierceneſs and Wrath of the Almighty God, and he hath on his Veſture and on his Thigh a Name written, <hi>KING of KINGS &amp; LORD of LORDS,</hi> and in his Hands is all the Power of the Earth, and alſo of the Heavens; for behold he makes all things new, old things muſt paſs away; for the Dragon having had Poſſeſſion for ſo many Dayes, even many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of the old Heaven, and alſo of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48769:7"/>
the old Earth, which I ſay the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Dragon having gotten the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion thereof, he by his Filthineſs defiled it, ſo that the true Virgin could no longer remain therein, but was driven forth of it, and was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed into the <hi>mourning and deſolate Wilderneſs,</hi> a place prepared her of God for ſo many Dayes, and her Heir which ſhe had brought forth, which is to rule the Nations with his Iron Rod, hath been caught up from her to God, and ſo the Dragon hath had the Dominion of the true Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin's Territories, ſince the Dayes of the Apoſtles, and hath made War with the Seed of the Virgin, and as it were overcome them, and in her Dominion he hath placed the great <hi>Whore,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots,</hi> and ſhe hath corrupted the Earth, and alſo the Heavens, wherein the true Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin was placed before ſhe fled into the Wilderneſs, the Whore having poluted them with the Filth of her
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48769:7"/>
                  <hi>Fornication;</hi> for her Superſcription is, <hi>Myſtery-Babylon the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots and Abominations of the whole Earth:</hi> And the Nations which the true Virgin's Heir ſhould have ruled, they have all been the Seat of this great VVhore, and ſhe hath guided them and rul'd them, as a man would guide and rule the Beaſt whereon he rideth, and ſhe hath made them all unſtable as VVaters, for ſhe ſate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Peoples, Multitudes, Nations</hi> and <hi>Tongues,</hi> and all the Kings of the Earth have committed VVhoredom with her, and have drunk of the Cup of her Fornication; for ſhe held forth a <hi>golden Cup</hi> in her Hand, a ſmooth Profeſſion and pleaſing Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, but within full of Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; yea, <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>poor, bond</hi> and <hi>free,</hi> even from the Beggar up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Dunghil to the Prince upon the Throne, they all drunk of this Cup, and have been drunken with the VVine of the VVhore's Fury;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48769:8"/>
and many of them have (as it were) drunk the Blood of the Saints and of the Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom he hath raiſed to bear their faithful Teſtimonies againſt the VVhore, and againſt her Fornications; and all the Blood that hath been ſpilt upon the Earth is to be found in her, for within her lodgeth the Ground of all Iniquity, and the Foundation of all Tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>But now hath the Lord God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred his poor baniſhed Spouſe, which ſits mourning in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the great Perſecution of her Seed; and great BABYLON is coming into his remembrance, and ſhe ſhall receive a juſt reward from the Lord God of Life for all the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations that have proceeded from her ſince the time the Virgin fled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Wilderneſs; &amp; though ſhe hath long ſate as a Queen, and hath known no Sorrow, but hath had a Husband, and hath brought forth many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48769:8"/>
of Fornication, and hath lived deliciouſly for many Generations, whileſt the true ſpouſe (the Lamb's Wife) hath ſate deſolate in the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Wilderneſs, where ſhe hath been childleſs and deprived of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, yet nevertheleſs <hi>thy Judgments</hi> are at hand, and thy <hi>Downfal</hi> approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, O thou great and <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Babylon;</hi> for Sorrow, Deſolation and Miſery is even ready to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee; and the Smoak of thy Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doth begin to riſe, and thy Kingdom is full of Darkneſs, and the Lord God hath diſcovered thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs and thy Sorceries, and thy falſe Divinations, whereby thou haſt deceived the Nations, and cauſed them to receive thy Beaſt like mark; and many are they that are come out from thee, and will no longer be partakers with thee in thy Sins, leſt they ſhould partake with thee of thy plagues; for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth thee; and thy Cup
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48769:9"/>
which thou haſt given to others ſhall be filled unto thee double, even the meaſure that thou haſt meaſured to others, ſhall be meaſured unto thy ſelf double, and all that wherein thy ſoul delighted muſt depart from thee <hi>and thou muſt come down and ſit in the Duſt, O thou Virgin-Daughter of BABY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LON;</hi> &amp; thou ſhalt be no more count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>delicate</hi> nor <hi>fair;</hi> for the <hi>DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CREE</hi> is gone forth againſt thee, and thy Judgment is aſſuredly coming upon thee.</p>
               <p>Therefore all ye Inhabitants of the Earth, hearken diligently and your Souls ſhall live, and take WARN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING in this the Day of your Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and go no longer on in your Polutions, but come forth of the midſt of BABYLON, and be no more partakers with her in her Sins; for, if you do, you will aſſuredly partake with her of her plagues; for ſhe muſt be burn'd up and conſum'd, and brought to nought by the fiery
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48769:9"/>
Fierceneſs of the Lord's Wrath; and the <hi>old Heavens,</hi> and the <hi>old Earth,</hi> wherein ſhe hath ruled in all this Dark Night of Apoſtacy ſince the Dayes of the Apoſtles, muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed with her, and all them that wilfully reſiſted the Voice of the Lord their God in their own Hearts and Conſciences, calling them out of <hi>BABYLON,</hi> the Land of Darkneſs, into his marvelous Light.</p>
               <p>Therefore beware of kicking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if in wilfulneſs and ſtubborneſs you reject this the large Love of God towards you, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs let it be known unto you all in his living preſence, that you have at large been warned, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhut not your Ears at the Voice of Peace, and be not like to the <hi>deaf. Add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> which ſtoppeth his Ear at the voice of the Charmer, although he charms never ſo wiſely.</p>
               <p>For now Wiſdom uttereth her voice in the <hi>open Street,</hi> and in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48769:10"/>
                  <hi>broad wayes,</hi> ſhe crieth at the Gates at Entry of the <hi>City,</hi> at the coming in at the Door, unto you O men I call, and my voice is to the Sons of man, <hi>O ye ſimple underſtand Wiſdom, and ye Fools be of an underſtanding Heart, and know in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s your day the things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to your Peace before they are hid from your Eyes, and the Door of Mercy be ſhut upon you, and the Decree ſealed againſt you, and Repentance removed far from you, ſo that you cannot attain to it, although y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u ſhould ſeek it with tears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as <hi>BABYLON</hi> comes to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, ſo likewiſe is the mariage of the <hi>LAMB</hi> prepared, and preparing, and his <hi>Bride</hi> is making her ſelf ready even the true Virgin, the Lamb's Wife <hi>(the true Church)</hi> is now retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the deſolate and barren <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> where ſhe hath ſate for many Generations in a mournful ſtate and condition, a place not known to the World, a place prepared her of God for ſo many Dayes; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48769:10"/>
now praiſes be unto the Lord our God, the Dayes are near expired, and ſhe is returning again into her former State and Glory; and the Lord is now creating for her a new Heaven, and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſheſs; and if any queſtion what her former Glory was, and wherewithal ſhe then was beautified? let them with ſingleneſs of Heart ſtand in the Light of the Lamb, look into <hi>John's</hi> Revelations, and there thou ſhalt ſee what he declareth of her, and of her Glory &amp; Beauty in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges paſt, even in his Dayes; for he ſaw her a woman exceeding glorious and beautiful, even cloathed with the Sun, having the Moon under her Feet, and on her Head a Crown of twelve Stars: She was clothed with the true Light of heaven, even with the brightneſs of the everlaſting day and the Moon with her changeable things was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Feet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſhe was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rowned with the Brightneſs of the Glory of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48769:11"/>
Lord God of Life, and ſhe travailed to bring forth the Man-Child that ſhould rule the Nations wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a Rod of Iron. Now this was the ſtate of the true Church in the Dayes of the Apoſtles, before the time of her Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment into the Wilderneſs: And <hi>John</hi> ſaw this to be wonderful, even in Heaven. Now this will be the State and Condition of the true Church after ſhe is returned out of the Wilderneſs again; and the time is aſſuredly come, where in the Lord God will cloath her with his own Brightneſs, and with his own eternal Glory, and ſhe ſhall again bring forth the Heir, which ſhall rule the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with his Rod of Iron, and ſhall bind PRINCES in Chains, and NOBLES in Fetters of Iron; and he that doth deny this, doth deny plain Scripture, for they bear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that <hi>Sion</hi> ſhall ariſe and ſhall ſhine for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, for her Light is come, and the Glory of the Lord is riſen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48769:11"/>
and ariſing upon her; and though the Darkneſs doth cover the Earth, and the groſs Darkneſs the People, yet the Lord ſhall ariſe upon her, and his Glory ſhall be ſeen upon her, and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall come to her Light, and <hi>Kings</hi> to the Brightneſs of her riſing, and ſhe ſhall awake, and put on her Strength and her beautiful Garments ſhall be put on; for hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there ſhall no more come into her the Uncircumciſed nor the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean; therefore <hi>cleanſe your Hands ye Sinners, and purifie your Hearts ye double-minded,</hi> that you may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted in this the Day of the Lord's l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rge Love and Mercies, that is ſo largely held forth and proffered unto you, to invite you, that you might not partake of the Plagues of BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYLON, which ſhall ſpeedily come upon her at unawares, in an Hour when you leaſt think of it ſhall Deſolation and Deſtruction come
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48769:12"/>
upon her, and upon all them that are found in her, partaking with her of her Sins.</p>
               <p>O therefore as you tender the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Welfare of your precious Souls, which ought to be counted as dear and as precious in your Sight as any Man's Soul that ever lived on the Earth; for they are precious in the Sight of the Lord; therefore prize them and this the Day of your Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, for you know not how ſoon the dark Night may overtake you, and you may be ſealed up in the Pit of utter Darkneſs, and no Means af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded you, whereby you may be redeemed into the Light again; therefore conſider of theſe Things while you have Time and Space, <hi>and come forth of</hi> Babylon, and touch no more of her Uncleanneſs, leſt you periſh eternally with her in your Stubbornneſs, and gain<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſaying the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48769:12"/>
VVitneſs of God in your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, which d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th ſtand a true VVitneſs againſt you in theſe things; and let not the long Forbearance of ſo merciful a God, whoſe Spirit hath for a long time ſtriven with you, and ſtill riſes up to condemn you in your own Hearts for your evil Deeds; I ſay, let not his long Forbearance harden your Hearts againſt the Day of Slaughter becauſe his Judgments are not ſpeedily executed upon you; for verily his Spirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with Man, but at laſt you will provoke his VVrath, &amp; cauſe it to be kindled againſt you, &amp; his fierce In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation will break forth of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den upon you, and <hi>Horror, Dread</hi> and <hi>Terror</hi> will take hold on all ſuch ungodly VVretches, which do De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight to his Spirit of Grace, which hath long ſtriven with them in their own Hearts and Conſciences, and have turned it into Laſciviouſneſs,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48769:13"/>
and VVantonneſs, and put the Day of the Lord their God afar off from them; yet let all ſuch know, that he is nigh unto every one of them, to ſmite them in their own Hearts and in their own Conſciences, for diſobeying of his righteous Law and juſt Command, which he hath clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made known unto them; <hi>for what may be known of God is made manifeſt in thee, for he hath ſhewed it unto thee, O Man:</hi> And though there hath been a long time of Darkneſs &amp; Ignorance, whereat the Lord hath winked; but now ſince the true Light hath ſhined in all Hearts ſo manifeſtly, ſo that none can plead Ignorance after they once come to be acquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: now doth he command all Men every where to repent, &amp; he that ſhall deny to obey his Commands ſhall be left without Excuſe in the Sight of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in the Sight of his Witneſs, which ſhineth in his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48769:13"/>
for the Commands of God are not grievous, but they that love him keep his Commandments, and meditate upon his Law Day and Night; for their whole Delight ſtandeth in walking in his Statutes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48769:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Man of Sin &amp; Death ſeparated from the Man of Righteouſneſs and Life, wherein the firſt m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> Adam <hi>is manifeſted to be of the Earth earthly, and the ſecond Man</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>to be from Heaven heavenly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THou that haſt any Longings or Breathings after the Lord God that made thee, and formed thee in the Womb, who ſtretched forth the Heavens as a Curtain, and by whom the Foundations of the Earth were laid; and thou that haſt any Thing in thee that is oppreſſed by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Power, and groans under the Burden of Oppreſſion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48769:14"/>
to be ſet at Liberty, even into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God; ariſe out of thy dark Slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, for the Night is far ſpent, and the dawning of the Day of the Lord God of Power is come, and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Son of Righteouſneſs is riſen and ariſing, even Chriſt Jeſus, the eternal Son of God, the Son of the everlaſting Day, who is the true Light of the World, and hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned every Man and Woman that cometh into the World with a Meaſure of his true Light, which Light ſhineth in the Conſciences of all the Sons and Daughters of Men, and this is the Light that lets thee to ſee the Thoughts of thy own Heart; <hi>For he that formed the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and created the Winds, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth unto Man his Thoughts, and the ſecret Intents of his Heart, whether they be good or evil;</hi> and this the Lord hath placed in thee to bear a true and faithful Teſtimony for him againſt every Appearance of Evil, &amp;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48769:15"/>
is God's Gift unto thee, which Gift is perfect and without Sin; for it is a true Meaſure of his Son Chriſt Jeſus, which hath enlightned every Man and Woman; this did never at any Time conſent to the ſpeaking of any evil Word, or the acting of any unrighteous Action by thee, or any other of the Sons or Daughters of Man, but hath and doth at all Times ſtand a Witneſs for the Lord God of Life, and hath at all Times been the Condemner of the Tranſgreſſor and the Worker of Iniquity <hi>in thee</hi> and them: Now fallen Man being Darkneſs it ſelf, having no Means whereby to diſcern his own <hi>Thoughts,</hi> yet this Light hath ſhined in the Darkneſs, but the Darkneſs could not comprehend it; therefore haſt thou and all Mankind for a long time walked in Darkneſs, and thy Deeds have been the Deeds of Darkneſs, and thou art become a Stranger to God and to his Wayes of Light and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48769:15"/>
Life, by Reaſon whereof thou loveſt Darkneſs rather then Light, becauſe thou loveſt thy own Will &amp; thy evil Deeds, which proceed from thence, whereby the Heritage of God in thee hath beenlaid waſte, &amp; his Righteous Seed oppreſſed and trampled under Foot in thee by the Power of Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs through thee; but now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his long Forbearance, and after many gentle Admonitions which he hath held forth to the Rebellious Sons and Daughters of Men; after all this is he appearing to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf known, and now are the Cries of the Oppreſſed entred into the Ears of the Lord God of Sabbath, and he is now jealous for his Seed's ſake, which hath long ſuffered under the Burden of Oppreſſion, and he is now manifeſting himſelf in this his great Day, to plead with all Fleſh in the Valley of Judgment; and he will <hi>Overturn, Overturn, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn,</hi> till he comes to reign, whoſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48769:16"/>
Right it is; for long hath the Powers of Darkneſs reigned in all Mankind, whoſe Right it was not; but now <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> making himſelf known, who is the true Light of the World, and he is ariſing to reign, whoſe Right it is.</p>
               <p>Therefore come into the Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſeriouſly conſider in thy own Heart how thy Condition ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before the Lord thy God, if thou were immediately called to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count before him for thy Deeds done in the Body, whether good or evil; and come but with an honeſt Heart to the Light of Chriſt Jeſus in thy own Conſcience, and that will let thee, and all the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men ſee how your Condition ſtandeth in the Preſence of your God; for be thou aſſured, that if the VVitneſs of God in thy own Conſcience condemns thee for thy evil Words and Actions, God from whence the Witneſs came is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48769:16"/>
greater, and will not any wayes ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie thee therein, but if thou give up to be guided by his Light in the Singleneſs of thy Heart, then thou wilt come into the Beginning of the Creation of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſee his Work dayly manifeſted <hi>in thee;</hi> and thou wilt come to ſee the Sword of the Lord God of <hi>Jacob</hi> to cut down &amp; to deſtroy the Tranſgreſſor at all times <hi>in thee,</hi> and thou wilt come to ſee that nature in thee that would ſtand up to take the Sword to kill or deſtroy thy Fellow-creatures, or oppreſs or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud any by the Unrighteous Power, thou wilt come to ſee that Nature to periſh by the Sword of the Lord in thee, which Sword is the Word of the Lord, which is a Diſcerner of the Thoughts of the Heart, and divides between the precious Thoughts and the vile, therefore as thou tenders thy own Soul, come to that Sword, and bring all thy Thoughts unto it, and in the Light thou wilt come to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48769:17"/>
ſee a nature in thee that hath a long time led thy Soul captive under the Captivity of Sin and Satan; and thou wilt come to ſee that nature carried away captive by the power of Chriſt Jeſus, even into the Land of Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; for he is now riſen in this his Day <hi>to lead Captivity captive,</hi> and to ſet free from all Oppreſſion, and now is the Day of his plenteous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption come, and his Salvation will he make known unto the Ends of the Earth, and will redeem all them that come to walk in his Light and that obey and follow it in all his motions, and that contentedly come to take up the Croſs daily to their own wills, and ſo in Singleneſs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt the Light, them will he redeem from under the Power of Sin and the Devil who is the Author thereof; and from the World and all its inticing Luſts; and as they give up wholely to be guided by the Light, and to take up their Croſs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48769:17"/>
daily, which croſſeth the carnal will, and ſo come to deny themſelves, and to follow Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World, whoſoever followeth me, ſhall not abide in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life;</hi> and he that comes into this, comes into the true Faith, which purifies the Heart, and they come to receive Chriſt, and to as many <hi>as receive him, to them Power is given to be the Sons of God,</hi> and ſo ſuch come to know what the Seed in them is, and what it is to have the tender Babe of Grace formed in them, and what it is to be born of God, and ſo ſuch do not commit Sin; for they have the Seed of God remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in them; <hi>for that which is born of God cannot commit Sin;</hi> for the Prince of this VVorld hath no part in this new Creature, who is created in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs.</p>
               <p>Now thou that art born after the Fleſh, and art in the firſt Nature, thou art a Stranger to this new Birth, which is born of God, and thou art
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48769:18"/>
ready with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> to cry out, <hi>Can a man ente, rnto his Mother's Womb a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain when he is old?</hi> or ſhall there any thing be brought forth by God whilſt man liveth upon Earth, to be made manifeſt to be without Sin? So thou art altogether ignorant of the wonderful works of the Lord; for the God of the world having blinded the Eyes, and darkned the Minds of all that live in the old nature, ſo that they therein cannot pleaſe the Lord their God, but their delight is in the works of Darkneſs, whereof the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is the Prince; and they love the world and the Glory thereof, <hi>and ſo the Love of the Father is not in them,</hi> but now if thou doſt but come to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the Light, and into true O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to it in tender Simplicity, thou wilt come into the ſpiritual warfare, and to march under the <hi>Banner</hi> of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> who is the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>CAPTAIN</hi> of our Salvation, and thou wilt come to ſee the Battle fought in Heaven between the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48769:18"/>
                  <hi>Lamb</hi> and the <hi>Dragon;</hi> even in God's Kingdom, which comes not by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, to ſay, lo here it is, or lo there it is; for his Kingdom is within thee, and there the Battle of the great God is to be fought, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt the Prince of Peace, and the <hi>old Dragon</hi> the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Now as Chriſt the Lamb of God comes to take away the Sins of the World, and to lead his Souldiers forth, he arms them with the whole Armour of Light, in <hi>Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Humility, Chaſtity, Soberneſs, and Gentleneſs, Love and Tenderneſs,</hi> contented in the Will of God toſuffer all things with Cheerfulneſs, ſo it may tend to his Glory<hi>:</hi> Now theſe are they which are to make War in Righteouſneſs againſt the Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Powers of Darkneſs in high Places, at whoſe Appearance all fleſh <hi>ſhall tremble,</hi> and all Hearts <hi>ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed;</hi> for Fearfulneſs ſhall ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the Hypocrites.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48769:19"/>
Now as <hi>Chriſt</hi> appears prepar'd to battle, and hath armed his Souldiers with thoſe Weapons afore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo likewiſe the <hi>Dragon</hi> he arms his Souldiers with his Armour, which is the whole Armour of Darkneſs, which conſiſts in <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Malice, Envy</hi> and <hi>Perſecution, Pride, Haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>High-mindedneſs, Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, Lying</hi> and <hi>Swearing, Defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>Deceit, Wantonneſs</hi> and <hi>Whoredoms,</hi> and many other wicked Weapons, which the Light will make manifeſt to them that abide faithful in it.</p>
               <p>Now let every one in particular come to a honeſt ſearch in your own Hearts, and examine your ſelves without Deceit, and ſee whoſe Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you are marching under, and whoſe Armour you wear; for it is but vain for any man to deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf any longer; for look whoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour thou beareſt, his Souldier thou
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48769:19"/>
art, and his Wages thou muſt look to receive; for if thou liveſt in Sin and Wickedneſs, thou art a Servant to Sin, and the Wages of Sin thou muſt expect to receive, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Sin is Death, therefore it were good for thee to ponder the thing wiſely, leſt thou bring thy Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon thy ſelf; therefore am I, out of the Tenderneſs of my Soul, and in bowels of Compaſſion towards thee, moved to warn thee, and to adviſe thee in dear and tender Love to the oppreſſed Seed in thee, which groans to be ſet at Liberty. Now the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of my Heart is, that thou ſhouldſt awake out of death, and come unto CHRIST the LIGHT, that he may give thee Life; and to caſt off every weight and burden, and the Sins that ſo ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly beſet thee; and that thou ſhouldſt put off the Armour of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and put on the Armour of light; for aſſuredly there is nothing that makes <hi>a Separation</hi> between thee and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48769:20"/>
thy God, <hi>but Sin;</hi> but now, herein ſtands the wonderful Love of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the fallen Sons and Daughters of Men, who were dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, and altogether in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without any Means or Hope of Recovery in themſelves; now the Lord beholding poor diſtreſſed man in this State, whereinto the Prince of Darkneſs hath captivated him, out of the Tenderneſs of his Compaſſion unto the poor diſtreſſed Sons and Daughters of men, he gave his only begotten Son into the World for a Light, and to every man and woman which is born upon the Face of the whole Earth, hath the Lord in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy given a meaſure of this true Light which hath enlightned every one which cometh into the World, in which Light ſtandeth the Power of God and in this Light man comes to ſee his Sins, and to ſee the Deceit of his own Heart, which otherwiſe he could not have ſeen; and though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48769:20"/>
thou art unacquainted with it, yet that is it that lets thee ſee the actings of the Prince of Darkneſs <hi>in thee;</hi> for if he plotteth in thee any miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Intents, whereby to deſtroy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man's Perſon or Eſtate, and ſo endeavours to make thee an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby he may do it ſecretly in the dark, and although no Eye of man can ſee thee, nor ſee his ſecret acting in thee, yet this Light will follow thee, and diſcover his ſubtil Deluſions unto thee, and make him many times appear odious unto thee, and calls thee and invites thee from following of him, and many times brings <hi>Fearfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Dread</hi> upon thee for thy wicked Actions; now this is that that would redeem thee out of Sin, which ſaves all them that believe in and follow the Son of God, the true Light of the World, out of Sin and Death, which is the Wages thereof.</p>
               <p>Now it is but vain for thee or any
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48769:21"/>
other to call Chriſt thy Redeemer and thy Saviour, and to ſay, that thou hopeſt to be ſaved by Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Death, becauſe he was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſixteen Hundred years ago, and yet thou liveſt in Sin and Wickedneſs, in Pride and Vain-Glory of this world, which paſſeth away as a Vapour of the Night afore the Morning Sun; but for all this, let me tell thee plainly without Deceit, nevertheleſs for all thy high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of thy ſelf, and for all thy vain Hopes and thy feigned Faith, thy Hope is the Hope of the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, which will periſh in the time of Trial, and thy feigned Faith can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give thee victory over the world, therefore if ever thou comeſt to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Redemption to thy Soul, thou muſt witneſs Chriſt's Death to kill Sin in thy mortal Body, and thou muſt witneſs his Reſurrection in thee.</p>
               <p>And as for his Sufferings at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48769:21"/>
I own according to the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Scriptures, but thou muſt witneſs him nearer to thee then at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> if ever thou wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs him to be thy Redeemer, and the Salvation of thy Soul.</p>
               <p>Now let me reaſon with thee a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Coolneſs and Moderation; if Chriſt be thy Redeemer, <hi>what is it that he hath redeemed thee out of, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou yet liveſt in Sin, and in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the World?</hi> And if he be thy Saviour, <hi>what hath he ſaved thee from, ſeeing thou art yet in Bondage to Sin and Iniquity?</hi> Therefore the ſting of death is not yet taken away while Sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, ſo thou canſt not call him thy Redeemer in Truth and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unleſs thou couldſt witneſs him to have redeemed thee out of ſin and tranſgreſſion, and thou doſt but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thy ſelf to call him thy Saviour, unleſs that thou couldſt witneſs that he did ſave thee out of temptations when they ariſe in thee from thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48769:22"/>
own Luſts, and ſo from Sin which they bring forth, and from Death which is the Wages thereof.</p>
               <p>Now as the firſt Nature hath reigned, which is of the Earth earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in all mankind, which is the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> over whom Sin came to have the Dominion, whereby Death came to reign over all Mankind in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſo now, as the Children of men come to be begotten into Chriſt the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo born of the new Birth of Righteouſneſs, they come to know <hi>what the Immortal Seed is,</hi> whereunto the Promiſes are <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> and come to witneſs Chriſt to be the Redeemer and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in Deed and in Truth, and that his Croſs in them is the Power of God unto Salvation, and they ſee, as they abide faithful in that which croſſes their own fleſhly wills, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they come to ſee the power of God and as they ſtand ſtedfaſtly faithful in it they come to ſee the Power of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48769:22"/>
Light in them, which is far ſtronger then the Powers of Darkneſs; for they come to ſee Victory in it over the Devil &amp; all his ſubtil Deluſions, and over the Fleſh and all its Luſts, and over the World and all the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities thereof, and as they abide in this Power, which is CHRIST, the <hi>Light</hi> of the World, and the Power of God unto Salvation, and as they follow him faithfully through all Sufferings, and all the Hatred and Malice which ariſes againſt them in the Children of Darkneſs, they will come to ſee him to trample down all his Enemies in them, and make them his Footſtool; but as any man or woman goes out of the Croſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſtandeth God's Power, and let their own wills rule in them, then they go into the Power of the Prince of the Air, which ruleth in the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Diſobedience, whoſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion wholely ſtandeth in man's cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and carnal will, and then he
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48769:23"/>
leads them captive at his own Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo as they ſtand in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion Sin comes to have Power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch in all his Motions, and then comes in Complainings and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings againſt the Lord, who made them; and ſo they come to cry out for want of Power, and becauſe they cannot have power and victory over Sin in their own wills, and in their own time, which is the very Ground wherein the Power of Sin ſtandeth; then when they ſee they cannot have Power over Sin there, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any to attain to unleſs they come out of the Power of their own will into that Power which croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it; then they come to plead for Sin in themſelves, then they not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Power over it there, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all others that they can never have Power over Sin, nor be ſet free from it whileſt they remain in this earthly Tabernacle; and then if the Lord raiſe up any to witneſs that he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48769:23"/>
hath redeemed them from under the Power of Sin, and ſo by his Power in them which is a Croſs to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal will of man, freed them from the Power of ſin and Death, then cry out thoſe that live in all manner of ſin and polutions, <hi>theſe are Deluders, take heed of being deceived,</hi> when, alas! there is nothing reigning in them that they can be deceived of but ſin and wickedneſs, and ſo they cannot bear the hearing that they ſhould be free from ſin until the Lord cut off them and their ſins together; but they never conſider that, <hi>as the Tree fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſo it lieth, and as Death leaves them,</hi> ſo aſſuredly <hi>ſhall Judgment find them; for in the Grave there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> neither can any unclean thing enter into God's Kingdom, which conſiſts of Purity, Holineſs, and Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Now the ſcriptures they declare <hi>that God is Light, and if we walk in the Light, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide in the Light, as he is</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48769:24"/>
                  <hi>in the Light, then we have Fellowſhip one with another, and the Blood of Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt cleanſeth us from all Sin.</hi> Now if thou comeſt into this <hi>LIGHT,</hi> this will let thee ſee that there is ſomething in thee that doth check, reprove and croſs thy own natural will, and this is the Power of God <hi>in thee,</hi> and would be unto Salvation if thou wouldſt but obey it; for it will cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie thy old Nature, and ſtand a Croſs over thy own will, and ſo keep it down, that it might not rule <hi>in thee,</hi> and ſo thy Soul will come to ſtand in the Power which is above the Power of ſin, and ſo come to be ſaved out of ſin, and out of Death, which is the ſting thereof: And ſo as thou comeſt into the Light, and therein ſtandeſt with an Upright Heart, the Light will make ſin and the Power thereof manifeſt unto thee in all its Motions, and will cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie all that is of the firſt Nature, and all that which ariſeth from thy
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48769:24"/>
ſelf, and will judge out that Power daily which hath moved in thee, and hath carried thee forth at all times to act contrary to the Mind and Will of God, and hath cauſed thee to oppreſs the Seed which God hath placed in thee; and ſo <hi>SION</hi> with the pure Seed of God <hi>in thee</hi> cometh to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed <hi>through Judgment,</hi> and her Converts come to bring forth a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Life and Converſation.</p>
               <p>Now thou that readeſt underſtand, <hi>The Life is more then Meat, and the Body is more then Rayment,</hi> and the <hi>pure Life</hi> is more then <hi>Knowledge;</hi> for <hi>old Adam,</hi> or the <hi>firſt Nature</hi> may eat of the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, and ſo by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t may come to talk much of the Truth, and what the Saints enjoyed in former Ages, but cannot come into the Life there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for he is driven out from the tree of Life into the earthly Imaginations without him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the <hi>ANGEL of the Lord with his flaming Sword,</hi> even <hi>the</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48769:25"/>
                  <hi>Righteous Law</hi> is placed to keep the Way of the Tree of Life leſt he put forth his Hand and take of the Fruit there of and eat, and ſo live forever: Now the firſt Nature is not to live forever, but for an appointed time; for that is the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and his Life which ſtandeth in ſin, and he hath tranſgreſſed the Righteous Law of God, and ſo hath ſinned, <hi>and that Soul that ſinneth muſt dye the Death,</hi> and ſo death cometh to reign over all Mankind from <hi>Adam</hi> till <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> from the firſt Nature till the Seed of God in the creature moveth under the burden of Iniquity, whereby it hath been preſſed down, as a Cart is preſſed with ſheaves, and comes to ſtir up the Creature, and draws him into ſome Conſideration, and brings him to underſtand his Condition, that he is even a Captive under ſin in the Land of Darkneſs, even in ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> and under many Luſts which are as ſo many hard Task-maſters to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48769:25"/>
him, and that he is but a ſtranger and a ſojourner there, and that the Lord hath promiſed him a land of reſt and freedom, but he knows not how to find it out until the Lord God ſhall raiſe up the <hi>great Prophet</hi> like unto <hi>Moſes</hi> to lead him out of this Land of Darkneſs through the red Sea, by his LIGHT, or PILLAR <hi>of Fire,</hi> which <hi>Light</hi> is Darkneſs unto the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi> even in their Day, which <hi>Pillar of Fire</hi> is to guide the Creature through the long deſert Wilderneſs into the land of reſt; and <hi>Moſes</hi> is till the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> they declare that there ſhall a REDEEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER come out of <hi>Zion,</hi> or the Seed of God within, who ſhall reign in Peace and Righteouſneſs over his own Houſe, which ſhall be raiſed up; for he will make them a willing People, and he will turn unto them the pure Language, and they ſhall all call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Name of the Lord <hi>with one Conſent,</hi> and he will bring back again
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48769:26"/>
their Captivity, and ſettle them in perfect Peace, ſo that they may eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſit <hi>under his own Vine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own Fig-Tree, and none ſhall make them afraid:</hi> And the <hi>Prophets</hi> they are till <hi>John,</hi> who is <hi>as the Voice of one crying in the Wilderneſs;</hi> now the VOICE ſaid, <hi>Cry,</hi> the Prophet anſwered, <hi>what ſhall I cry? That all Fleſh is Graſs, and the Clory of man as the Flowers of the Field, therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Way of the Lord, and make ſtreight the crooked Paths, and let the high lofty Mountains of Man's proud Will be laid low, and let every Valley, and low deſpiſed Place be raiſed, that ſo the ranſomed of the Lord may paſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>John</hi> he baptizeth to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and bringeth the Creature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Sorrow and a Trouble, becauſe it cannot bring forth Fruit worthy of Repentance, and he declares that he is not the <hi>Meſſias</hi> that is to come after him, which is to be preferred before him, whoſe Shoe-latchet he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48769:26"/>
was not worthy to unlooſe, but that he is ſent to bear his Teſtimony of him, and <hi>John</hi> he is till Chriſt, and when he comes which is the true Meſſias, and the true Redeemer of the promiſed Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Spirit, who is the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and the true Prophet like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom the Lord hath promiſed ſince the Dayes of old, even this is he that ſhall come out of <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſhall bring Deliverance unto that Seed in all the Sons and Daughters of Men that hath long groaned, and that which <hi>Sion</hi> hath long travailed with, and been in Pain to be delivered from under the Burden of Oppreſſion; and he will crucifie the old Nature, even the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who hath been the Oppreſſor, and nail him to the Croſs, and ſo by the Croſs to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd to his corrupt Will will mortifie or kill his Deeds, even by the Power of the Spirit, which Power ſtandeth in that which croſſes the old Nature; now
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48769:27"/>
the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Life, that ſtandeth in Sin, and in Tranſgreſſion, and in Deceit and Guile, which are all the Fruits of Death, whereon he feeds, and is in ſome ſort ſatisfied, for he dares not approach unto the Tree of Life, becauſe the Angel of the Lord's Preſence ſtandeth with the flaming ſword ready lifted up, even the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law, which ſtill layes hold on him when at any time he approaches near unto the Tree of Life, this cuts him down, ſo that he at all Times remains in Death, and feeds upon the Fruits thereof; this is the true State and Condition of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> who hath loſt himſelf, and is fallen from God his Maker: But now the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> whom the Lord is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, and whom he hath created, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven after his own Image, in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and true Holineſs, who was and is the firſt born among many Brethren, even Chriſt the Son of the living God, who puts an End to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48769:27"/>
Tranſgreſſion, and deſtroyes Sin, and ſayes, <hi>O Death I will be thy Death,</hi> and fulfills the Royal Law in all things, and paſſeth through the flaming ſword, for the Fire cannot touch him, but he has free Acceſs to the Tree of Life, and feeds plentifully upon the Fruit thereof, and ſo lives forever, and nothing will ſatisfie him but the very Life it ſelf: And this is the true Condition of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who is the true Heir of all things: Now he that comes to have this Babe begotten in him, that which hath begot him will bring him forth; for ſhall I bring to the Birth, and not bring forth? ſaith the Lord; now he that comes to be born of this Birth, and to have his Life to ſtand in this, he ſhall with this come to eat of the Tree of Life; for this is he that ſhall enter in at the ſtreight Gate into the City whoſe Builder is God: Therefore if thou feeleſt any thing in thee which ſtirs
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48769:28"/>
and moves in thee againſt ſin, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the very Appearance of Evil, there lies the ſeed out of which this Babe is formed; and therefore as it is as yet but weak, as in Appearance to thee, thou oughteſt to be tender over it, even more tender then the Mother that is newly conceived is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the tender Fruit of her Womb, and beware of bruiſing of it, and of ſmothering of it, for a ſmall thing will offend it and choak it; but as thou art tender over it, and with Carefulneſs doſt cheriſh it, and come to take Delight in it, thou wilt find it to grow daily, and encreaſe in thee from ſtrength to ſtrength; but thou muſt beware that thou doſt not at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time lay any Burden upon it, whereby it may be offended, for if thou doſt, thou wilt come into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for the ſame, and thou wilt come to ſuffer Loſs in thy ſelf, which Loſs will not eaſily be regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for thou wilt find Deadneſs and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48769:28"/>
Barrenneſs to ariſe up in thee, and the Dread and Terror of the Lord will take hold daily upon thee; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Lord hath executed his Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon that which hath oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſeed; for thou muſt aſſuredly come to know a day of Vengeance in thee to light upon the Head of the Tranſgreſſor, and a Night of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, before thou canſt know the day of Joy and Gladneſs.</p>
               <p>Therefore if thou wilt give up freely to let the Seed of God go free to ſerve the Lord its God in Truth and Righteouſneſs, and wait in Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſee the Oppreſſor judged and condemned in thee, and to ſee the Vengeance of the Lord to be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Head of the Tranſgreſſor, and ſo to become one with that which judgeth, and executes the fierce Wrath and Indignation of the Lord upon that which oppreſſeth the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Seed in thee<hi>:</hi> Now if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one with the Lord in this, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48769:29"/>
give up thy ſelf willingly in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, then a ſhort Work will the Lord make in the Earth, and thou ſhalt come to ſee him whom thy Soul loveth, who now doth but ſpring up in thee, as a Lilly among Thorns, but when he comes to be brought forth, he will be the fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt amongſt ten thouſand, and this is <hi>Chriſt in thee,</hi> the Hope of Glory, and thou wilt come to live <hi>in him,</hi> and he <hi>in thee;</hi> and ſo thou wilt come to live in the Life that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sin was, and before Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was, and ſhall be when Sin and Tranſgreſſion is deſtroyed, and ſhall be no more; and then thou wilt come to witneſs old things to be done away, and all things to become new, a new Heaven and a new Earth wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs; and thou wilt come to witneſs God's Will to be done in thy Body of Earth as it is in Heaven, and his Kingdom in thee to be come and eſtabliſhed,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48769:29"/>
and his Power made known <hi>in thee</hi> to the deſtroying of the Power of Sin and Satan, and his Glory to be made known <hi>in thee</hi> to the ſetting forth of his eternal Praiſe in the midſt of all his Enemies; and this is declared by many who are faithful Witneſſes of it, according to the Meaſure which the Lord hath freely been pleaſed to give and beſtow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and this do they witneſs to be an eternal Truth, according as the Spirit of the Lord God of Truth hath revealed it unto them; for they never received <hi>from Man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Man, but by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who leads into the Path of Light and Life all that are willing and obedient to follow him; now theſe things are deep and hidden My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries to them that yet remain in Darkneſs; but if thou canſt but read the Scriptures ſingly without adding thereunto thy own or any other Mans Imaginations, they teſtifie of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48769:30"/>
him that hath the Life in him, and they declare how the two Births have been brought forth in all Ages, which Births came from the two Seeds, even the Seed of the Promiſe and the Seed of the Serpent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two Seeds there is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Enmity placed, ſo that they can never be reconciled one to the other, but ſtill ariſe one to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the other; but at laſt the Seed of the Woman muſt and will get the Victory, for that muſt come to bruiſe the Seed of the Serpent's head, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the other bruiſe his Heel for a ſhort Space; now ſee the Seed of the Serpent brought forth by the firſt Birth in <hi>Cain,</hi> how the Enmity comes to work in him, ſo that he came as it were to murder <hi>Abel,</hi> the ſecond Birth, which was brought forth of the Seed of the Promiſe, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was it, but becauſe the Sacrifice that was offered up by the promiſed Seed was accepted, and his, the Seed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48769:30"/>
of the Serpent was not; therefore <hi>Cain,</hi> the firſt Birth, who as in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to his outward Birth after the Fleſh was therein his Brother; but yet he being ruled by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray Seed to <hi>Abel,</hi> the Enmity cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to riſe up and to murder in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Abel,</hi> and then he became a Fugitive and a Vagabond upon Earth all his Dayes, not having an Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in God, although he builded a City, and call'd it by his Son's Name; ſo here the Seed of the Serpent brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Seed of the Woman's Heel, and yet the Serpent's Head was brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this thing<hi>:</hi> See the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and there thou ſhalt ſee it more nearly and clearly made manifeſt unto thee; for there thou may'ſt ſee the two Seeds Placed together in one fleſhly Womb, and there they ſtrove which ſhould firſt come forth to the Birth; I know thou canſt not but with me witneſs theſe two Seeds in thee, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48769:31"/>
which ſhall be brought forth; now rough <hi>Eſau</hi> came firſt forth in the Birth, who became a Hunter, and hunted up and down after Veniſon, and became a rough hairy Man, of whom it was ſaid, <hi>The Elder ſhall ſerve the Younger</hi> before they had been inſtrumental to do Good or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil; then after him <hi>Jacob</hi> was brought forth, who by true Interpetation is a Supplanter, who ſtayed at home with his Father, who in Proceſs of Time came to get both the Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and the Bleſſing, for the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Right belongeth to him, for he was bleſſed in the Womb, for in him the promiſed Seed ſprung up, who at laſt became a great People; yet was he by <hi>Eſau</hi> long kept out of the Birth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>right, although that <hi>Eſau</hi> had ſold it to him, and counted it a ſmall thing, even a thing of nought, and ſold it for a thing of ſmall Value, even for a Meſs of Pottage, which
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48769:31"/>
afterwards he would have ſought the Bleſſing with Tears, but could not attain it; but the Power of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> daily increaſed, ſo that he became a mighty people, and the Dread and the Terror of the Lord was with him, which cauſed the <hi>Heathen,</hi> even the Stock of <hi>Eſau,</hi> even many times to fear, and tremble, and ſtand aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at their Preſence: Yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs this fleſhly Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which came out of his fleſhly Loins, came to be corrupted, and the Seed of the Serpent came to bear Rule in many of them, ſo that the Seed of God came to be oppreſſed in them, which ſhould have born Rule over the Seed of the Serpent in their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies, ſo that many times there was hardly one to be found in an Age, or one in a Generation which came to witneſs the Serpent's Head to be bruiſed in him, or that the Seed of God ruled in him in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleneſs
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48769:32"/>
and ſimplicity; ſo that the Lord came as it were to be forgotten amongſt the Sons and Daughters of Men; but yet there was the Seed within, which ſtill breathed and groaned after God, for which ſeed's ſake the Lord hath long waited, that he may be gracious unto the Sons and Daughters of Men, otherwiſe he had long ago conſumed them in his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and his fierce Wrath had broke forth upon them, as it did upon <hi>SODOM</hi> and <hi>GOMORRAH,</hi> and all the Cities of the Plains.</p>
               <p>But he hath at all times raiſed up his own ſeed in ſome, ſo that they have born their faithful Teſtimonies for him againſt the ſeed of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and ſo by them came to give forth Laws and Statutes, whereby the Children of Men may come to know his Mind and Will, ſo that in the Performance of them <hi>they ſhould li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> but they that diſobey the ſame <hi>ſhould dye</hi> the Death, then all
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48769:32"/>
they which were of the Seed of <hi>Jacob</hi> after the Fleſh ſaid, that whatſoever the Lord ſhould command them, they would perform; but the Lord full well knew that there was not ſuch an Heart in them, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to cry out, <hi>Oh that there was ſuch an Heart in this People to obey me, then ſhould their Peace break forth as the Morning, and their Righteouſneſs as the Sun at Noon-day;</hi> but the Lord's all-ſeeing Eye ſaw that there was the Seed of the Serpent ſtill lodging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them and in them, which ſoon afterwards ſhewed it ſelf forth, which cauſed the Lord's Wrath to break forth upon many of them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to their Deſtruction: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Lord had wrought great Deliverances for them, even in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying them down into the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and cauſing them there to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a hard time of Servitude and Bondage under the Hand of <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hard Task-maſters; and raiſing up
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48769:33"/>
his own Seed to ſhew it ſelf amongſt them, even to the redeeming them out of the Land of Bondage, and from under their <hi>Egyptian Captivity,</hi> even by many grievous <hi>Plagues</hi> and mighty <hi>Wonders,</hi> which he ſhewed forth upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hoſt; and carried them through the Depths of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> as upon dry Land, and deſtroyed <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Multitude, who purſued after them, and led them through the <hi>Deſart Wilderneſs,</hi> and cauſed Water to guſh cut of the <hi>Rock</hi> to ſatisfie their thirſty Souls, and fed them many Years with <hi>Manna</hi> in the Wilderneſs; yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs for all this his large Love towards them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this pure Seed of God was ſtill oppreſſed in many of them by this Seed of the Serpent, which cauſed the Lord to deſtroy many Thouſands of them in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, before they came into the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land; ſo that there was but a very ſmall Number of them that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48769:33"/>
came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that entred into the Land of Reſt, even but <hi>Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> which were JOSHUA and CALEB; for all the reſt were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, becauſe the Seed of God was oppreſſed <hi>In them,</hi> even by the Seed of the Serpent, which cauſed them <hi>To complain,</hi> and <hi>To murmur,</hi> and to depart from his <hi>Statutes,</hi> and rebel againſt his <hi>Righteous Laws;</hi> yet ſtill the Seed of God cryed and groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto him under all this, and his Ears are continually open unto the Cryes thereof; and for this Seed's Sake he raiſed up a People out of the Stock of JACOB, even in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, which he cauſed to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of Promiſe.</p>
               <p>And whenas they ſtood faithful in his <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Statutes,</hi> he deſtroyed their Enemies before them, even in a wonderful and miraculous manner, ſo that in proceſs of time they came to have victory over all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and to ſit down in the Land, in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48769:34"/>
Reſt and Peace, and the Lord made them a Dread and a Terror to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about them, and they built ſtrong Holds and great fenced Cities, ſo that they became a mighty People; &amp; as they ſtood faithful unto the Lord, he made them as a <hi>Sign,</hi> and as a <hi>Wonder</hi> unto all the Nations of the Earth, ſo that his Fear and Dread fell upon many that had been Strangers to (and alienated from) him; &amp; they were ſet as a City upon a Hill, which could not be hid, but ſtill there was the Seed of the Serpent lodging in many of them; for when they were brought to ſit down in Reſt and Eaſe, the Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent came to riſe in them, and the pure Seed came to be oppreſſed, and the pure Simplicity, that came to be loſt, and they rebelled againſt the Lord, &amp; tranſgreſſed againſt his pure Laws &amp; Statutes; and they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Whoredom, even with the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> and then the Lord raiſed up his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48769:34"/>
Seed in his Prophers, and ſent many of them unto them, to fore-warn them of the Deſtruction that would come upon them, if they ſtill went on in their Rebellion againſt the Lord<hi>:</hi> And as the Lord had ſet the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whileſt they ſtood in his Statutes, as a <hi>Sign,</hi> and as a <hi>wonder</hi> unto the Nations round about them, ſo now likewiſe he hath ſet his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, in whom his Seed is raiſed, as <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> to the Houſe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> becauſe they were become a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious People; but many of the Prophets they murdered, wherein the ſame Seed of the Serpent that was in <hi>Cain</hi> appeared; and ſome they caſt into <hi>Priſon,</hi> others they <hi>Bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> ſo that they provoked the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to Wrath, ſo that he let looſe the <hi>Heathens</hi> againſt them, and ſuffered them to deſtroy their Land, and to lay waſte their fenced Cities, and to carry them away Captives in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrange Lands, till he had humbled
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48769:35"/>
them, and brought them low; then, when they were in Diſtreſs they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon him, &amp; cry'd unto him in the time of their Trouble, and his Ears were open to them, and then he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times by his Prophets came to reaſon with them, and to lay open before them the many Deliverances which he at ſundry times had wrought for them, &amp; of the Largeneſs of his Love towards them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; yet how they had all along rebelled againſt him, and turned his Righteous Law behind their Backs, and not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Reproofs; but yet, when he by Afflictions had brought down the Seed of the Serpent, ſo that they came low in Heart, and in Mind to be humbled towards him, and to let the oppreſſed Seed in them to ariſe, whoſe Sighs and Groans were to the Lord, for whoſe Sake the Lord brought back again their Captivity, and cauſed them to reſt in their own Land, in Peace, and Safety; and when
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48769:35"/>
he had ruled them many Years by Judges, then they deſired to have a KING, even as all the Nations round about them had, who were Strangers to God, and in this they provoked the Holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but yet for his own Seed's Sake he ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all this and much more, <hi>And gave them a King in his Wrath,</hi> even <hi>Saul</hi> the Son of <hi>Kiſh,</hi> and anoynted him with his own Spirit, that he might have Underſtanding and Wiſdom to rule and govern them, that they might walk humbly in the Statutes of the Lord; but he himſelf ſoon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed the Voice of the Lord, when he was ſent to deſtroy the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites,</hi> that he ſhould not ſpare old nor young, but ſlay both Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Infant and Suckling, Ox and Sheep, Camel and Aſs; but ſee how the Seed of the Serpent aroſe in <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and caus'd him to diſobey the Commands of God, by ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> (the King of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48769:36"/>
the <hi>Amalekites) alive, and the beſt of the Sheep and of the Oxen, and of the Fatlings, and of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ambs, and all that was Good,</hi> and would not utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, but every thing that was vile and refuſe, that they deſtroyed utterly, and ſo provoked the Spirit of the Lord which anoynted him King; and the Lord repented that he had ſet up <hi>Saul</hi> King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he rent the Kingdom from him, becauſe his pure Seed came to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in him; and ſo, as <hi>he gave</hi> [thoſe People] <hi>a King in his Wrath, he took him from them in his Sore Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then he ſent his Servant <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> whom he anoynted to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet unto the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſent him unto <hi>Saul,</hi> to acquaint him that the Lord had rent the Kingdom from him; and the Spirit of the Lord departed from him, and with it his Honour; but yet, behold the Subtilty of the Serpent in him, who
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48769:36"/>
would have tempted the Prophetto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have honoured him before the Peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, when that in him, to which the Honour did duely belong, was depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him; but herein the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent's Head (in ſome Meaſure) came to be bruiſed: Then the Lord ſent his Prophet to anoynt <hi>David</hi> King over <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who was the Son of <hi>Jeſſe;</hi> for ſaid the Lord, <hi>Behold, I have found a man after my own Heart to reign over</hi> Iſrael; to whom the Lord promiſed, that out of his Loyns, after the Fleſh, ſhould come the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> that ſhould rule over the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that there ſhould not want one to ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> henceforth, even forever, and that his Kingdom ſhould be an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, and of his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion there ſhould be no End, and the Government ſhould be upon his Shoulders; this is the great Prophet that <hi>Moſes</hi> foretold of to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that ſhould come, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48769:37"/>
                  <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up from among your Brethren, like unto me, him ſhall you hear in all things, and it ſhall come to paſs, that he that will not obey the Voice of this Prophet ſhall be cut off from amongſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now conſider what this <hi>Moſes</hi> was, who declareth this unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he was one whom the Lord preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Court of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> which was of the ſtock of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and by his Hand the Lord brought many Plagues upon the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and by him delivered the Seed of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of their Captivity.</p>
               <p>So likewiſe, this Prophet that the Lord hath promiſed to raiſe up, like unto him, from amongſt their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, even from within the midſt of every man, which ſhall bring JUDGMENTS and PLAGUES up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> even the Land of Darkneſs, &amp; bring Deliverance unto the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which now
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48769:37"/>
groans under the Burden of Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> even CHRIST, all the Prophets pointed at him, and propheſied of his Coming, even in the one Body of Fleſh; for they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, <hi>That a Virgin ſhould conceive and bear a Son, and they ſhould call his Name</hi> EMANUEL, <hi>which by Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is, GOD WITH US;</hi> and he promiſed <hi>To give him for a COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NANT unto the People, and for a LIGHT unto the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>that he might be his Salvation unto the End of the Earth;</hi> and that he ſhould put an End unto all <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which then the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, &amp; were commanded ſo to do, even by the Lord their God, and had their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> their <hi>Levites,</hi> their <hi>Burnt-Offerings</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> their <hi>Heave-Offerings,</hi> their <hi>Peace-Offerings,</hi> their <hi>Shew-Bread,</hi> their <hi>Paſſeovers,</hi> their <hi>New-Moons,</hi> their <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> their <hi>Solemn-Aſſemblies,</hi> their <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Altar,</hi> with the <hi>Ark</hi> of the <hi>Teſtament;</hi> but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48769:38"/>
yet all <hi>Theſe</hi> were but <hi>Shadows</hi> of things which were to come; for the Subſtance was and is <hi>CHRIST;</hi> for the Seed of God was yet (for all this) oppreſſed in them; for they ſmote with the Fiſt of Wickedneſs, and many times provoked the Lord to Wrath, ſo that he deſtroyed many of them, and they cauſed him to ſay, that though the number of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in number as the Sands on the Sea Shore, yet ſhould there be but a Remnant of them ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which Remnant was them in whom the pure Seed of God came to be raiſed up to bear Rule, and ſo they came faithfully to believe in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, and ſo by Faith they came to be ſaved; for they came to witneſs it to give them Victory over Sin, and ſo they believed in Chriſt the Son of God, which was to come, &amp; to be made manifeſt to the World in general, and was manifeſted in them in particular; and of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48769:38"/>
all the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> believed, in the Notion, and in a Carnal Senſe, but yet in Proceſs of time, when he came they would not receive him; for the Seed of the Serpent raiſed up in them a Heart of Unbelief, ſo that they were hardned againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe when he came unto them.</p>
               <p>And although the Wiſe Men &amp; the Aſtrologers could tell <hi>Herod,</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Place and time, when and where he ſhould be born, and although the Lord did ſend his Prophet, even <hi>John,</hi> to bear witneſs of him, and in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them into Repentance, and ſo to prepare the Way before him, ſo that many of them believed, that <hi>John</hi> was ſent of God; and although he declared, that <hi>there was one coming after him whoſe Shoe-latchets he was not worthy to unlooſe,</hi> yet their Hearts were hardned by the Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which ruled in them; ſo that when Chriſt was brought forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who was and is the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48769:39"/>
true Redeemer of the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> even the Seed of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, for which Seed's ſake the Lord hath all along ſpared them, and his fierce wrath has been withheld from breaking forth upon them, ſo that they were not utterly deſtroy'd from being a People; but yet his Wrath broke forth ſoon after upon them, which burnt in Fury like the Fire, till it had conſumed them, and cut them off from being a People, and ſcattered them up and down the Earth as Vagabonds, becauſe of their Hard-Heartedneſs &amp; Unbelief, which aroſe in them from the Seed of the Serpent, becauſe they rejected him whom the Lord had ſent to bruiſe the Serpent's Head; but before they came to be cut off, do but behold the Seed of the Serpent how it came to work in them in the Enmity againſt the Seed of the woman<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even <hi>CHRIST,</hi> and how in ſubtilty, aſſoon as <hi>Herod</hi> came to hear of his Birth, under a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48769:39"/>
pretence of worſhipping, him he would have ſlain him, but the Lord delivered him out of his Hands, by ſending him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained till after <hi>Herod</hi>'s Death.</p>
               <p>But yet, ſee how the Bloody Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent's ſeed was raiſed up in <hi>Herod,</hi> which cauſed him to cauſe all the Children in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> to be ſlain; but yet, after his Death CHRIST JESUS came to be made manifeſt unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even in the Land of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> and at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in all the Regions round about, even by diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and the Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law, in their Synagogues &amp; in their Temple, who confounded them by grounded Reaſons &amp; ſtrong arguments, making it appear to them by Scripture, and by evident Signs, and miraculous Wonders, which he wrought amongſt them, that he was the <hi>Meſſias</hi> that was to come, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Scripture declared, and many there were that believed in him, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:48769:40"/>
that forſook all to follow him, even of the poor, fooliſh &amp; deſpiſed by the world; but yet the Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſtill ruled in the great, mighty and potents of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Fleſh, and in the wiſe <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and the Rulers of the People, ſo that their hearts were hardened, that they could not believe, becauſe he came not according to their Expectations in their carnal Imaginations; for ſaid they, <hi>When Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt cometh, who ſhall know from whence he comes? but for this Fellow, we know from whence he is: is not this the Carpenter's Son whoſe Father and Mother, Siſters and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are amongſt us daily?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So, becauſe he came not according to their proud Wills, which could not ſtoop to ſo mean a thing as the <hi>Carpenter's Son,</hi> although the Lord had declared by a Voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that <hi>he was his beloved Son, in whom he was well pleaſed,</hi> and that they were <hi>to hear him;</hi> yet ſtill they were
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:48769:40"/>
carryed on in Hatred againſt him by the Enmity from the curs'd ſeed that reigned in them; and them in whom the Seed of God came to bear rule, which confeſſed Chriſt to be the <hi>Son of God,</hi> were <hi>hated, deſpiſed</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>curſed,</hi> becauſe they knew not the Law, and turned out of their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues; and the Enmity encreaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (daily) in them againſt him, ſo that they (daily) ſought Oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to take him, that they might put him to Death; but yet they durſt not lay hands on him, becauſe his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time was not yet come: Now the Prieſts and the Chief Leaders of the People cauſed them to err, ſo that the Scriptures (came to be fulfilled) which declared, <hi>That he ſhould be a Man of Sorrow, and one acquainted with Grief, and be deſpiſed and rejected of men, and that they ſhould hide as it were their Faces from him, and eſteem him as ſmitten of God and afflicted;</hi> ſo
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48769:41"/>
the People then cryed out, <hi>That he caſt out Devils by the power of</hi> Beelze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub, <hi>the Prince of Devils;</hi> others they cryed out, <hi>He was a Companion to Publicans and Sinners;</hi> others, <hi>That he was a Sabboth-breaker;</hi> others cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>He hath a Devil; why hear ye him?</hi> So there came many falſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations to be raiſed up againſt him by the ſeed of the Serpent, and the Enmity which he raiſed up in them, whoſe <hi>Head</hi> Chriſt came <hi>to bruiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet, notwithſtanding all this, many were they that believed on (and followed after) him, amongſt whom he declared the Meſſage unto them which the Lord had ſent him to declare, which was, <hi>That he was the Light of the World, and that whoſoever follow'd him ſhould not abide in darkneſs, but ſhould have the Light of Life; and that for Judgment he was come into the world; and that the Prince of this world might be judged, which ſhould come after</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:48769:41"/>
                  <hi>him, but had no part in him; and that he that had formerly had his Sight might be blind, and that he that had been blind might receive his Sight.</hi> And he did many Miracles amongſt them, even Raiſing the Dead, cauſing the Lame to walk, and the Blind to ſee, and the Deaf to hear, and the Leper to be clenſed; and he exhorted them, <hi>To walk in the Light whilſt they had the Light, that they might be the Children of the Light; and that they ſhould work while they had the Day, for the Night ſhould come wherein no man could work.</hi> And he told even the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees,</hi> That the Kingdom of God came not with Obſervations, that is to ſay, Lo here it is at this place, or lo there it is at that place, but that the Kingdom of God was nigh at hand, even <hi>within them,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he often exhorted them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and many times ſpoke to them in Parables, comparing the Kingdom of Heaven to a Grain of <hi>Muſtardſeed,</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48769:42"/>
which ſhould be ſown in the Earth, which is the leaſt among many Grains, yet it ſhould ſpring up into a <hi>great Tree,</hi> wherein the Fowls of the Air might rooſt; and he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to a loſt Groat, which could not be found till the Woman had lighted the Candle and ſwept her Houſe; and he compared it to a certain <hi>Lord,</hi> who went into a far Country, who called his own Servants, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto them his Goods, and unto one he gave five Talents, and unto another two, and unto another one Talent, to every man according to his ſeveral Ability, and ſtreight-way took his Journey, then he that had received the five Talents went and traded with the ſame, and made them other five Talents, and likewiſe he that had received two gained alſo other two; but he that had received one, went and digged in the Earth, and hid his Lord's Money; after a long time the Lord of thoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48769:42"/>
cometh, and reckoneth with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo he that had received five Talents came, and brought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther five Talents, ſaying, <hi>Lord, thou deliveredſt unto me five Talents, behold I have gained beſides them five Talents more;</hi> his Lord ſaid unto him, <hi>Well done thou good and faithful Servant, thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>een faithful over a few things, I will make thee a Ruler over many things, enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord;</hi> and he alſo that had received two Talents came, and ſaid, <hi>Lord, thou deliveredſt unto me two Talents,</hi> behold <hi>I have gained other two Talents beſides them;</hi> and his Lord ſaid unto him, <hi>Well done thou good and faithful Servant, thou haſt been faithful over a few things, I will make thee Ruler over many, enter thou into the Joy of thy Lord;</hi> then came he which had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the one Talent, and ſaid, <hi>Lord, I knew thee, that thou art an hard man, reaping where thou haſt not ſown, and gathering where thou haſt not ſtrewed, &amp; I was afraid, and went and hid thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:48769:43"/>
                  <hi>in the Earth, lo there thou haſt that is thine;</hi> his Lord anſwered and ſaid unto him, <hi>Thou wicked and ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servant, thou knoweſt I reaped where I ſowed not, and gathered where I ſtrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not, thou oughteſt therefore to have put my Money to the Exchangers, and then at my coming, I ſhould have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved mine own with Uſury; take there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Talent from him, and give it to him that hath ten Talents; for unto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that hath, ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance; but from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away even that which he hath; and caſt ye the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Servant into utter Darkneſs, where ſhall be Weeping, and Wailing and Gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi> And he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Kingdom unto <hi>Ten Virgins<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and to many other things, which would ſwell into a great Volumn to declare and open the Myſteries there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>Now all this was to be found <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:48769:43"/>
                  <hi>man;</hi> for there he told them the Kingdom was, whereunto this was likened; and he adviſed them, <hi>to ſtrive to enter into the Kingdom;</hi> and told them, <hi>The Gate was ſtreight, and the Way was narrow, which leads into it; but the Way was broad, &amp; the Gate wide, that leads into Deſtruction:</hi> yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs for all this, the god of the World blinded their Eyes, and their Hearts were ſtill hardened, although there were ſome that bore witneſs to their Faces, whom they had ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt to ſeek to enſnare him by Words, and teſtified, <hi>That never man ſpake like unto him,</hi> yet for all this the Enmity came to burn the more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently in them againſt him, which Enmity aroſe from the Seed of the Serpent which lodg'd in them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſought Oportunity that they might by any Means put him to <hi>death</hi> which was not unknown to him, <hi>who was the expreſs Image of God the Father,</hi> in whom the Godhead dweltbodily;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48769:44"/>
ſo that he was the Searcher and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerner of the Heart, and by his Light he makes manifeſt the Secrets there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; for he ſaw through the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> who made large Profeſſion of God the Father, but yet they rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Son of God, whom he had ſent a <hi>Light into the World,</hi> therefore he pronounced Wo againſt them, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, <hi>Blind Leaders of the Blind,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>Whited Walls,</hi> and likening them unto <hi>Painted Sepulchres,</hi> which outwardly <hi>made a fair ſhew,</hi> but inwardly <hi>were full of Rottenneſs,</hi> telling them, that they waſhed the Outſide of the Platter, but the Inſide remained full of Filthineſs, and that they paid <hi>Tythes</hi> of <hi>Cummin, Mint</hi> and <hi>Anniſe,</hi> when they omitted the weightier Matters, even <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> theſe are they that in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Appearance did walk as to the Law blameleſs, yet Chriſt warn'd his Diſciples to beware of the Leven of theſe great Profeſſors, who did all
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48769:44"/>
to be ſeen of Men, they made <hi>Long Prayers</hi> in the Synagogues, and loved the Chiefeſt Place in the Aſſemblies, and Greetings in the Market-place, and would not keep Company with <hi>Publicans</hi> nor <hi>Sinners,</hi> but cry'd out againſt Chriſt, becauſe his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples did eat with <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> yet nevertheleſs, Chriſt told his Diſciples, that unleſs their Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs did exceed the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theſe High Profeſſing <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> they ſhould in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of Heaven: and he many times did diſpute with theſe Profeſſors, who ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Chair, but they being Carnally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded could not underſtand him, becauſe he ſpoke unto them in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Senſe, therefore what was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him unto them was as Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, which they could not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and many times his Sayings were ſo hard amongſt them, that them that believed on him could not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48769:45"/>
underſtand; for even his Diſciples, whereof he had choſen twelve par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly unto himſelf, many times asked him in private, what might be the Meaning of what he had ſpoke to them in publick: And he ſent forth many of his Diſciples to declare his Name abroad in the World, and that they ſhould publiſh, That CHRIST, the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias,</hi> who was the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of the World, which the Prophets propheſied ſhould come, that <hi>now he is come a Light into the World, that whoſoever believes in him ſhould no longer remain in Darkneſs;</hi> and he fore-told to them the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their <hi>Temple</hi> and <hi>Temple-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips,</hi> and that he was come to put an End to it all, and that they ſhould no longer worſhip him at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor in the Mount at <hi>Samaria,</hi> but he that will worſhip the Father, <hi>muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> and that ſuch the Father ſeeks to worſhip him; and that <hi>God</hi> was and is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48769:45"/>
thoſe that <hi>will worſhip him, muſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in Spirit and in Truth;</hi> and he told his Diſciples, that he had choſen them twelve, and yet one of them was a Devil, and he fore-told them, that he ſhould be betrayed by one of them into the Hands of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and that they ſhould be all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended becauſe of him; but honeſt-hearted <hi>Peter,</hi> who was one of the 12. told him from the <hi>pure Simplicity</hi> that lodged in his Heart, that <hi>though they all ſhould forſake him, yet he would not;</hi> but Chriſt ſaw how ſecretly the Seed of the Serpent lodged in him, &amp; ſo anſwered him, <hi>that before the Cock ſhould crow he would deny him thrice;</hi> and he told them, <hi>that the Shepherd ſhould be ſmitten, and the Sheep ſhould be ſcattered,</hi> and that the Chief Prieſts and Elders ſhould take him by Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; hale him before the Judgment-Seat, that he ſhould (by them) be put to Death, and that the third day he ſhould riſe again, &amp; that he would
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48769:46"/>
go before them into <hi>Galilee,</hi> and that no Man could take away his Life, but that he laid it down that he might take it up again; for he had Power to lay it down, and Power to take it up again, all which came to paſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he had ſaid; for the Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtill aroſe amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt him from the ſeed of the Serpent, which lodged in them, and cauſed them to combine with the Chief Prieſts and Elders, who hired <hi>Judas Iſcarriot,</hi> even one of the twelve, to betray him into their Hands for thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pieces of Silver, and ſo came with a Band of Soldiers, and with a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Kiſs betrayed him into the Hands of Unreaſonable Men, who came forth with Pikes and Staves, as if he had been a Murderer, whenas he daily taught in their Synagogues, and diſputed with them in their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and no Man laid hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; but now was the Time come wherein the ſeed of the Serpent muſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48769:46"/>
bruiſe his Heel, and he muſt bruiſe the Serpent's Head; for he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared his Life unto a Corn of Wheat, which when it was ſowed in the Ground was but one, but when it ſprung up it came to be many; and he ſaid, that <hi>the Son of Man muſt be lifted up, and when he was, he ſhould draw all Men after him;</hi> and he told his Diſciples, that <hi>he would come again unto them, and be with them unto the End of the World, and that he would not leave them comfortleſs, but he would ſend them the Comforter, even the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, which ſhould lead them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth, and bring all things to their Remembrance,</hi> and that <hi>he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the World of Sin, of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and of Judgment;</hi> and that <hi>he was the good Shepherd, that would lay down his Life for the Sheep,</hi> and that <hi>all the reſt were but Thieves and Robbers, whoſe own the Sheep were not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, thou that readeſt, do but conſider and behold how mightily
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48769:47"/>
the Enmity which is placed betwixt theſe <hi>Two Seeds</hi> works in each of them one againſt the other, ſee how the Seed of the Serpent ariſeth to bruiſe the Seed of the Woman's Heel in the Diſciples of Chriſt, and them that had believed in him, when he was betrayed, and taken and bound and ſent away to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat, how the Seed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent raiſed up Doubtings, and Fear, and Queſtionings in them, whether he were the CHRIST yea or nay, whereby the pure Seed of God in them came as it were to have its Heel bruiſed for that preſent time, &amp; they all forſook him, except <hi>Peter</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in whom the Seed of God was raiſed up in ſomething a higher Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then the reſt; but yet in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of Tryal, when he cane to be queſtioned concerning Chriſt the Seed of the Serpent raiſed up in him a ſlaviſh Fear, which cauſed him to deny <hi>Chriſt,</hi> even with Oaths; but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48769:47"/>
then the Cock cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, and he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Chriſt's Words, and he went forth and <hi>wept bitterly:</hi> Now ſee alſo the Strivings that were betwixt the <hi>Two Seeds</hi> in <hi>Pilate,</hi> how from the honeſt Simplicity of the Seed of God which lodged in him, he conſeſſed, he <hi>found no Fault in him whom they called the King of the</hi> Jews, but would have looſed him from the Bands of Death; but yet ſee the Workings of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Serpent in him, which raiſed up a Fear in him of diſpleaſing the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe Mouthes were continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opened unto him, crying out, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with this Fellow, crucifie him, he is not worthy to live upon the Earth:</hi> Now behold what a ſtreight <hi>Pilate</hi> was in between two, even in himſelf; they cryed out, <hi>That they would have Chriſt crucified, and</hi> Barabas <hi>the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer delivered to them,</hi> and his Wife ſent to him, <hi>That he ſhould have no hand in the Death of that juſt man; for She had been much troubled in a Dream</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:48769:48"/>
                  <hi>concerning him,</hi> and that of God in his own Conſcience teſtified unto him, <hi>That he was innocent of the things whereof he ſtood accuſed before him;</hi> then the Seed of the Serpent roſe up in him, and cauſed him to work wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs in Hypocriſie, and cauſed him to call out unto the People, and to tell them, that he would not have any Hand in the Death of this man, but that his Blood ſhould be upon them, and upon their Children, and they all cryed out that it might be ſo, ſo <hi>Pilate</hi> called for Water, and waſhed his Hands, and ſaid, <hi>That he was innocent, as concerning the Blood of this Juſt Man;</hi> and ſo he delivered him unto them to be crucified, who formerly had great Strivings in his Body of Fleſh, in ſo much that it cauſed him to ſweat Drops of Blood; ſo likewiſe now upon the Croſs the Seed of the Serpent ſo bruiſed his Heel whereat he cryed, <hi>MY GOD, MY GOD, why haſt thou for ſaken me?</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:48769:48"/>
but at his Departing, when he yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up the Ghoſt, then the Seed of the Woman began to riſe to bruiſe the Serpent's Head, when the Vail of the Temple rent, and the Rocks clave, and the Graves opened, and many of the Saints that had ſlept came forth, and Darkneſs came over the Earth; then Fear and Dread fell upon the Hearts of many, and the Serpent's Head was bruiſed down in them, ſo that they confeſſed, that they belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>he was the Son of God:</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they buried him in a ſtrong Sepulchre, and rolled a mighty Stone upon the Mouth thereof, &amp; although the chief Prieſts and Elders ſealed it with their own Seal, and ſet Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers over it to watch him, leſt any Man ſhould ſteal him away in the Night, yet the third Day he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, according to the Scriptures, in ſuch a Miraculous Manner, that the Sight thereof ſtruck Dread and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement upon the Souldiers, which
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48769:49"/>
cauſed them to for ſake the Sepulchre and to go and tell it to the Chief Prieſts and Elders, yet ſee the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the Serpent, how it wrought in them to cover the Guilt from the ſight of Men, and how he turned his Head to ſave it from bruiſing, in cauſing them to give the Souldiers Money, that they might go their way and report, <hi>That whileſt they were aſleep his Friends came and ſtole him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them;</hi> yet nevertheleſs he appeared unto many after he was ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from the dead; for the Bands of Death could not hold him<hi>:</hi> And the firſt which ſaw him after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was <hi>Mary,</hi> who ſtood weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without at the Sepulchre, and Jeſus ſaid unto her, <hi>Woman, why weepeſt thou? who ſeekeſt thou?</hi> She ſuppoſing him to be the Gardener ſaid unto him, <hi>Sir, if thou haſt born him hence, tell me where thou haſt laid him, and I will take him aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto her,</hi> Mary, <hi>ſhe turned her</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:48769:49"/>
                  <hi>ſelf and ſaid unto him,</hi> Raboni, <hi>which is to ſay, Maſter, Jeſus ſaid unto her, touch me n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, but go unto my Brethren, and ſay unto them, I aſcend unto my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and your Father, and to my God &amp; your God;</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> came and told the Diſciples, that ſhe had ſeen the Lord, and that he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken theſe things unto her; and now the Seed of the Woman was raiſed up mightily to bruiſe the Serpent's Head: He afterwards app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Diſciples at ſundry times and Places, bidding them to go and preach the Goſpel to all Nations; &amp; he told them, that <hi>he would be with them to the End of the World,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and there to wait till they ſhould receive Power from on high, even the Holy Ghoſt the Comforter, which he had promiſed to them before; and he told them, that after the Holy Ghoſt was come upon them, <hi>They ſhould be Witneſſes unto him, both in</hi> Jeruſalem
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48769:50"/>
                  <hi>and in</hi> Judea, <hi>and in</hi> Samaria, <hi>and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth,</hi> which accordingly came to paſs, when they were met together with one accord, on the Day of <hi>Pentecoſt;</hi> for there ſuddenly came a Sound from Heaven, as of a ruſhing migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Wind, and it filled all the Houſe, where they were ſitting, and there appeared upon them cloven Tongues as of Fire, and ſate upon each of them, and they were all filled with the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with other Tongues as the Spirit gave them Utterance; and there were dwelling at <hi>Jeruſalem Jews,</hi> devout men out of every Nation under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and now when this was noiſed abroad the Multitude came together and were confounded, becauſe that every man heard them ſpeak in his own Language, and they were all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed, and marvailed ſaying one to another, <hi>Behold, are not all theſe that ſpeak</hi> Galileans, <hi>and how hear we every</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:48769:50"/>
                  <hi>man in our own Tongue wherein we were born, we do hear them ſpeak in our own Tongues the Wonderful Works of God; and they were all amazed and in doubt, ſaying one to another, what meaneth this!</hi> Now the Seed of the Woman was raiſed up in many of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout men, and the Serpent's Head came to be bruiſed; but yet there were others in whom the Seed of the Serpent ruled, which cauſed them to mock and to ſay, <hi>Theſe men are full of New Wine,</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> was raiſed up amongſt them by the Power of the Almighty to declare unto them the Eternal Truth of God, whereby the Serpent's Head came to be bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in many, and the Seed of God to be raiſed up, even in three thouſand, whoſe Souls were then converted; and the Seed of the Woman ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed more and more, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles went on in the Dread and in the Authority of the Lord, declaring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Nations what tho Lord had
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48769:51"/>
made manifeſt in them, even by the Operation of his Powerful Spirit; &amp; they turned People from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of the Serpent, even Satan, to the Power of God, which was Chriſt in them the Hope of Glory; and they told Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that Chriſt was in them except they were Reprobates; yet they met with ſtrong Oppoſitions, even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them and without them, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe from the Seed of the Serpent, but yet they witneſſed the Croſs of Chriſt to be the Power of God to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Now do but behold how ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly the Seed of the Serpent came to be deſtroyed in <hi>Paul,</hi> even by the Seed of the Woman, who bruiſed his Head, who being a violent Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came ſuddenly to be convinced, even by the Voice of Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World, which Light ſhined round about him, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Blind to what he had formerly ſeen, and that Eye which formerly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48769:51"/>
was blinded, came to be opened and that Eye which formerly had been opened came to be ſhut, and the Scales fell from off them, and that Tongue that had formerly been drunk came to ſound forth the Praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the Lord in the Declaration of his glorious Goſpel; and not only <hi>Paul,</hi> but whole Nations, came to be converted unto God, &amp; to be turned from Darkneſs unto the Light of the glorious Goſpel, and the Sound of God's mighty Day went through all the Earth; this was a good Day, wherein Chriſt warn'd his Diſciples, that they ſhould work; but yet this Day was to be darkned; for Chriſt told them, <hi>That the Night ſhould come wherein no man could work;</hi> for he ſaw, that the Seed of the Serpent yet lodged in many of them, who then profeſſed him, therefore he gave his Diſciples Warning of them, and told them by what Signs they ſhould know them, which were, <hi>That they</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:48769:52"/>
                  <hi>ſhould come in Sheeps Clothing,</hi> a fair outward Shew, but inwardly raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Nature of the Sheep, and the Wolfiſh Nature ſhould lodge in them, which would make a Prey of the Sheep, and continually ſeek to devour them; and this Nature did ariſe from the Seed of the Serpent which lodged in the Hearts of many, and came afterwards to work in a Myſtery, even in the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and this was the man of Sin, which ſate in the Temple of God, as God, and exerciſed himſelf above all that is called God, which was then vailed and not known, except unto a few, to whom the Man of Sin came to be revealed, and the Everlaſting Day of the Lord came to be known, and they came to give forth their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony from the Seed of God which was raiſed up in them, that the Ends of the World were come upon them, and that the latter times were come, whereof Chriſt had fore-warned
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48769:52"/>
them wherein Antichriſt ſhould come, and that he was then in their Dayes come; and that there were many Antichriſts then gone forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, which Antichriſts made up the one great Antichriſt in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, and they declared, that the Myſtery of Iniquity did then in their Dayes begin to work; and that the Form of Godlineſs ſhould come to be followed, and the Power of Godlineſs to be denyed<hi>:</hi> And the Apoſtle exhorted the <hi>Theſſalonians, Not to be troubled, neither by Word, nor by Spirit, nor by Letter, as from us, that the Day of Chriſt is at Hand:</hi> So he declared, that there ſhould be a Night; for elſe he had not ſpoken of a Day to be at hand, which Night was then drawing on, therefore he adviſed the afore-ſaid <hi>Theſſalonians, Not to let any man deceive them by any Means, as concerning the Day of the Lord;</hi> for that Day ſhould not come except there came a Night, or a Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48769:53"/>
away firſt, that the Man of Sin might be revealed, the Son of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which Man was conceived from the Seed of the Serpent, who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; ſo that he as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God, ſhewing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he is God, <hi>even the God of the world, who blindeth the eye of the mind of many.</hi> And the Apoſtle declared unto the fore-mentioned People, that the Myſtery of Iniquity did already work, only he who now letteth would let until he were taken out of the Way, &amp; then ſhould that wicked one be revealed, whom the Lord would conſume with the Spirit of his Mouth, and deſtroy with the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Coming. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles declared, <hi>That Perilous times were at hand, and ſhould come, wherein men ſhould be Lovers of themſelves, more then Lovers of God,</hi> and that they ſhould be <hi>Proud, Heady, High<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>minded</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:48769:53"/>
                  <hi>men, and ſhould have a Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ſhould deny the Power;</hi> they ſhould be ſuch, who <hi>ſeek after filthy Lucre, and through Covetouſneſs ſhould make Merchandize of Souls for diſhoneſt Gain,</hi> and they ſhould be <hi>Fierce, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of them that are good,</hi> and ſhould <hi>ſpeak Evil of Things they know not, but what they know, is naturally, as Bruit Beaſts, and in thoſe Things they corrupt themſelves; theſe are Murmurers and Complainers, walking after their own Luſts, and their Mouthes ſpeaking great ſwelling Words, having mens Perſons in Admiration, becauſe of Advantage; theſe are as raging Waves of the Sea foaming out their own Shame, Wandering Stars, to whom is reſerved the Blackneſs of Darkneſs forever, therefore the Wo is unto them; for they have gone in the Way of</hi> Cain, <hi>and run greedily after the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of</hi> Balaam, <hi>even for Gifts and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards:</hi> And <hi>Enoch</hi> the Seventh from <hi>Adam</hi> propheſied of theſe, ſaying, <hi>Behold, the Lord cometh in Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:48769:54"/>
                  <hi>of his Saints to execute Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon all, and to convince all that are Ungodly amongſt them, of all their Ungodly Deeds, which they have ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly committed; and of all their Hard Speeches, which Ungodly Sinners have ſpoke againſt him.</hi> Now theſe were the Miniſters of Darkneſs, therefore they have wrought in the dark, &amp; their Deeds have been the Deeds of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and theſe are they that have kept People in Blindneſs and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſome Thirty, ſome Forty and ſome an Hundred Years, even all their Life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>time, ever learning, but they never came to the Knowledge of the Truth by them, and theſe are they which have taught for Doctrine the Precepts of Men, and their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are contrary to the Scriptures, and are as followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They tell People, That the Scriptures are the Word of God, when there is no ſuch thing mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scriptures; but they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48769:54"/>
that Chriſt was the Word, which was in the beginning with God, and was God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> They tell People of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſome of them of ſeveral Sacraments, and of Three Perſons in the Trinity; when the Scripture declares no ſuch thing; yet the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and holy Ghoſt we own, which is but one.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> They Sprinkle Infants with Water, and tell the People, They are adopted into Chriſt, and are thereby become Members of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when there is neither Command nor Example in all the Scriptures for any ſuch thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> They tell People, That the Firſt Day of the Week is the Sabbath Day, and ought to be kept more holy then any other Day; when there was no ſuch thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Chriſt nor any of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>5thly,</hi> They have told the People,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:48769:55"/>
That the Houſe made of Lime and Stone is the Church, and the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, wherein the Lord dwels; when the Scripture declares no ſuch thing, but the Contrary, that is, that <hi>God dwelleth not in Temples made with Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>6thly,</hi> They taught the People to obſerve Dayes and Set Times, as <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>mas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>day,</hi> and <hi>Children<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>mas-day,</hi> and <hi>Lamm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s-d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y,</hi> and <hi>Candle-mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> and <hi>Michael's-mas-day,</hi> with <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and their <hi>Good Fryday,</hi> and their <hi>Whitſuntide,</hi> and <hi>Shrovetide,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other <hi>Saints Dayes,</hi> which are te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious (here) to mention, whereof the Scripture makes no mention.</p>
               <p>And they have told the People, That <hi>Tythes</hi> and <hi>Offerings</hi> are due to them, and <hi>Easter-Reckonings,</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer-Dues,</hi> and <hi>Smoke-Pennys,</hi> and <hi>Reek-Pennys,</hi> and Money for <hi>Eggs</hi> and <hi>Gardens,</hi> with their great fair <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Glebe-Lands,</hi> whereby they, their Wives and Families, may live
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:48769:55"/>
even in the Sins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> which were Pride, abundance of Idleneſs and Fulneſs of Bread.</p>
               <p>Now this, which they call their Dues, is the very Pillar and Ground upon which their Goſpel and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry ſtands; for let this be but taken away, and down fall they, with their Goſpel and Miniſtry, which ſome of them have not been aſhamed to declare in publick.</p>
               <p>Now the Scripture declares not any ſuch thing, neither is there any mention made of ſuch Maintenance to be Compelled from the People to maintain them that are the True Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, who are Called and Choſen, and ſent abroad from Country to Country, and from City to City, to declare the Glorious Goſpel, that the Sound thereof might reach even to the Ends of the Earth; and as they received freely, ſo they were to give freely; and into what City ſoever
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:48769:56"/>
they came, they were to enquire who was worthy, and there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main eating ſuch things as were ſet before them; <hi>for, the Labourer is worthy of his Meat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, thou that readeſt, conſider in thy own Heart; thinkeſt thou that the Lord God of Life hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted his Glorious Goſpel in the Hands of ſuch Hirelings, as before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, who would not declare it to the Poor and Needy, whereunto it is the Glad-Tidings of Salvation, becauſe they have not wherewithal to ſatisfie them for it? Nay, verely nay; the Lord never intended any ſuch thing; but he ſent his Prophets to cry out to every one that thirſts, that they might come unto the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and take Wine and Milk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Money and without Price. And <hi>John</hi> witneſſes that the Spirit ſaith Come, and the Bride ſaith Come, and whoſoever is athirſt may come,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:48769:56"/>
and take of the Water of Life free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, That he did not eat any Man's Bread for nought, but wrought with Labour and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, Night and Day, that he might not be Chargeable to any; but he commanded, that if any would not Work, neither ſhould he eat. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Maintenance was not ſo large, neither did they ſit down in one Place to preach the Goſpel, ſome Ten, ſome Twenty and more years, and ſo ſit at Eaſe in Pride and Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, compelling their Maintenance from the People, and making Friends to the Rulers &amp; Magiſtrates, having their Perſons in Admiration that they may have the Advantage of the Law againſt the People, that they may have their Goods by Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and caſt their Bodies into Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if they Refuſe to put into their Mouthes, to ſatisfie their Luſts, as thoſe which have ruled in this long Night of Apoſtacy have done. But
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:48769:57"/>
the True Apoſtles, who laboured with their own Hands, and travail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up and down in Hunger and in Cold, who were counted as Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and not worthy to live upon the Earth, by them in whom the ſeed of the Serpent ruled; they fore-told the People, that ſuch Ravening Wolves ſhould come, who ſhould make a Prey upon the Sheep; and as there had been Falſe Prophets in all ages before them, even ſo there ſhould ariſe Falſe Teachers amongſt them, who privily ſhould bring in Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bringing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves ſwift Deſtruction, and many ſhould follow their pernicious Ways, by reaſon of whom the Way of Truth ſhould be evil-ſpoken of; &amp; through <hi>covetouſnes</hi> they ſhould with Feigned Words make Merchandize of the People: And they likewiſe declared, That in the Latter Times there ſhould come Scoffers, walking
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:48769:57"/>
after their own Luſts, &amp; ſaying, <hi>Where is the Promiſe of the Lord's Coming? for ſince the Fathers fell aſleep all things continue as they were from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Creation:</hi> And theſe were they who had forſaken the <hi>right way,</hi> and gone aſtray following the Way of <hi>Balaam</hi> the Son of <hi>Boſer,</hi> who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Wages of Unrighteouſneſs; theſe are Wells without Water, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven broken Ciſterns that can hold no Water, Clouds that are carried with a Tempeſt, to whom the Miſt of Darkneſs is reſerved forever; for, while they promiſe Liberty to others they themſelves are Servants to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               <p>Now, many Years were not to be expired before theſe ſhould come, who were the Antichriſts and the Falſe Chriſts; for the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> declared, that the Latter Times were then, even in his dayes, in theſe words, ſaying, <hi>Little Children, it is</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:48769:58"/>
                  <hi>the Laſt Time, and as ye have heard, that Antichriſt ſhall come, even now are there many Antichriſts, whereby we know that it is the Last Time; they went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would</hi> (no doubt) <hi>have continued with us; but theſe went out that they might be made manifeſt that they were not of us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, theſe Antichriſts were they who had been amongſt the Apoſtles, and in Fellowſhip with them, as to Outward Appearance, ſo that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they came to get the Form of Godlineſs, but had not the Life nor the Power.</p>
               <p>Now, do but behold how ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſeed of the Serpent came to work in them againſt the Seed of the Woman, even ſecretly, as in a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, whereby it could not ſo eaſily be diſcovered as it had formerly been; for now it had as it were a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:48769:58"/>
Covering to hide it ſelf under, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Form of Godlineſs, and a Likeneſs of Truth: for thoſe Falſe Apoſtles went forth from the True Apoſtles into the World, and the World received them, and went af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them; ſo that in proceſs of time the Form of Godlineſs came to be followed, and to be cryed up in all the Earth, and the Life and Power thereof to be loſt and forgotten.</p>
               <p>Now, the Seed of the Serpent lodged under the Form or Likeneſs of Truth, but could not lodge in the Truth it ſelf; for therein lodgeth the Seed of the Woman, which is to bruiſe his Head; ſo that under the Form and Likeneſs of Truth he has made War with the Truth it ſelf; and where-ever the Seed of God hath appeared in any, they have been deſtroyed by them in whom the ſeed of the Serpent ruled; <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>Revelations</hi> ſaw it all in a Viſion, he ſaw that which had whored from
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:48769:59"/>
God to make War againſt the True Spouſe, and to drink the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt, and to cauſe all (to worſhip her) both great and ſmall, rich and Poor, high and low, bond and free, and to receive her Mark, and thoſe that refuſed it came to be ſlain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, where Satan's Seat is; and now the Glorious Sun was ſet, and the Night was come whereof Chriſt had fore-warned his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and Truth was as it were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from the Earth, ſo that in length of Time that ſeed that had whored from the Life and Power of Godlineſs came likewiſe to depart from the very Form of Godlineſs alſo; for the ſeed of the Serpent hath not any Love to the Form of Godlineſs, but only becauſe it could not ſo well come (as it were) to eat out the Life and the Power any other wayes; but now it even departed from the Form likewiſe, and came
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:48769:59"/>
to ſet up Invented Traditions, which is, to worſhip Saints, and Images, and the like, which is not any part of the Form of Godlineſs, but of the old <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Worſhip under which the ſeed of the Serpent for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly lodged, which was to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Sun, Moon and Stars; and ſuch like vain things.</p>
               <p>And now, when at any time the Lord raiſed up his Seed in any to bear their Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Wayes and Cuſtoms of Men, and to make manifeſt the Way of Truth, according as the Lord hath revealed it unto them; then the Seed of the Serpent ariſeth in them in whom it rules, and cauſes them even to Murder, Deſtroy or Baniſh them, according as the Lord permits; and thus hath the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ruled in all this long Night of Apoſtacy, ſince the Dayes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and caus'd Millions of Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands to be Murdered for ſatisfying
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:48769:60"/>
of Luſts. Now, this was a Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer from the Beginning, therefore all that croſs his Kingdom will he Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Deſtroy; for, by him the Lamb of God was ſlain, who was Dead and is alive, and liveth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>Now, thou that readeſt, do but look into theſe latter Times, even within theſe few Years, and thou ſhalt ſee how the ſeed of the Serpent hath made a Prey of thoſe in whom the Seed of God hath been raiſed; ſee in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s dayes, what Burning, what Impriſoning, what Torturing was there exerciſed upon them who had the <hi>ſeed of God</hi> raiſed up in them, &amp; could not Worſhip the Beaſt, in vvhich the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent lodged, nor receive his Mark, they rather chuſed to bear all that could be inflicted upon them; ſo that by their Means the ſeed of the Serpent came again to be diſcovered, ſo that he was feign in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:48769:60"/>
to creep under the Form of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs again, whereby to Shelter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to ſave his Head from brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>Now behold the Weapons of theſe two Seeds; for as their Natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s are Contrary one to the other, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are their Weapons; for the ſeed of the Serpent's Weapons are Carnal, and therefore he hath exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed his Tyranny upon the outward, fleſhly or carnal Bodies of them in whom the Seed of God hath been raiſed: And the Saints, in whom the Seed of the Promiſe hath been raiſed, their Weapons are Spiritual, and Mighty through God, to the throwing down of the ſtrong Holds of Sin; and they War not with Fleſh and Blood, neither do they any harm to mens Perſons, but they war with Principalities and Powers, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Wickedneſs in high Places; ſo that when the ſeed of the Serpent has exerciſed his Cruelty at any time
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:48769:61"/>
upon their carnal or fleſhly Bodies, they have not at any time reſiſted in the leaſt, but have born and ſuffered all in Patience, knowing that therein they were to poſſeſs their Souls; ſo that by their Patience the Serpent's head hath (many times) been bruiſed, whereby they have (as it were) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained victory over their Enemies. Now look but back ſince the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Charles</hi> late King of <hi>England</hi> his reign, and there thou mayeſt ſee how the ſeed of the Serpent hath been (by the ſeed of God) chaſed out of one Form into another, and how he hath ſhifted to and fro to ſave his Head from bruiſing<hi>:</hi> See in <hi>Charles</hi>'s time how the ſeed of the Serpent lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Biſhops and Prelates, and how it was drawing out of the Form of Godlineſs again into the <hi>heatheniſh</hi> Way of Worſhip; but ſee how the Lord hath (then) raiſed up a People, in whom his ſeed was manifeſt, who bore their Teſtimony againſt thoſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:48769:61"/>
Biſhops and Prelates, in whom the contrary ſeed lodged, who came to be hated, and in ſcorn and deriſion called <hi>Puritants,</hi> and were rendered by them (as Separates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Deceivers &amp; Deluders) in whom the ſeed of the Serpent ruled; for therein lies the ſubtilty of the Serpent, to charge the Truth with that, which he himſelf is guilty of; ſo that at all times the ſeed of God and his eternal Truth hath been perſecuted (by the Serpent and his ſeed) under the Name of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror Hereſie and Blaſphemy. So thoſe People came to be impriſoned, fined, and many of them baniſhed; but yet ſee how the Judgments of the Lord came both upon King, Biſhops, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Prieſts, and how the Serpent came to have his Head bruiſed in them, who raiſed up a War in the Nation, whereby they came to be cut off from the Face of the Earth, and all ſtood in a tottering Condition, ſo that the ſeed of the Serpent was fain
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:48769:62"/>
to endeavour to ſhelter himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a more ſmoother Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs then he had done in many years before, even under the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Form<hi>:</hi> but then the Lord raiſed up his ſeed in a People, who could not be ſatisfied under that Form; for the Light, even Chriſt, ſhined in them, and let them ſee many groſs Errors in it, and cauſed them to with-draw from having Fellowſhip with them; and theſe in ſcorn came to be called (by the rude Multitude) <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants;</hi> but they alſo came ſoon after into a Form, ſo that there was a ground in them wherein the ſeed of the Serpent might lodge, therefore it ſoon entered into that Form, and likewiſe corrupted it: but then the Lord raiſed up his ſeed again in ſome of them, and cauſed them to depart from them, out of that Form, and to give their Teſtimony againſt the Errors thereof, which aroſe from the ſeed of the Serpent; and theſe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:48769:62"/>
came by the rude Multitude to be called <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> but theſe ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the pure Life, that aroſe in them from the ſeed of God in them, and came into Imitation of what the Saints of God had done in former Ages, and ſo came into a Form of Godlineſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Life and Simplicity, which firſt moved in them, came to be loſt, and there came a ground wherein the ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent could lodge, therefore he ſoon entred into that Form<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and likewiſe corrupted it, yet the Lord ſtill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him with his Light, which ſhined in theſe dark Forms, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many of them to ſee that there is nothing but Emptineſs and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs in that Form, and that their Souls (therein) could not be ſatisfied; and then they came into a more pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Way, and Likelineſs of the Truth, then any of the former, and they bore their Teſtimony againſt all the Forms through which they had
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:48769:63"/>
come; for they ſaw (by the Light of Chriſt) the Deceit that lodged in them, and ſo they came to a Way of ſeeking, and waiting on the Lord; but yet they likewiſe came (again) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Form, and there was a kind of a ground amongſt them, wherein the ſeed of the Serpent could remain; for the Serpent can turn himſelf into the likeneſs of any thing, even into the very likeneſs of the Way, the Life, &amp; the Truth; but though he can tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf into the Form of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Light, and into the Likeneſs of Truth, yet he cannot come into the Way, nor into the Life it ſelf, nor into the Truth, therefore now is the Lord raiſing up a People after all this who ſhall worſhip him in Spirit &amp; in Truth, out of all Forms &amp; Likeneſſes, ſo that in them the Lord will deſtroy and judge out all that ground, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſeed of the Serpent can lodge, ſo that the Serpent's Head is come to be bruiſed in many Thouſands in
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:48769:63"/>
their particulars, and as it is begun in the particulars, ſo likewiſe it ſhall at length be bruiſed in the general, &amp; the ſeed that hath long groaned unto God ſhall be delivered from under the Burden of Oppreſſion; for now af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this long dark night of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which hath been for this 1600. &amp; odd years, wherein the Lord has been as it were a ſtranger unto the Sons &amp; Daughters of Men, and they have lived (as it were) without God in the World, taking pleaſure and delight in the vanities thereof, &amp; their fooliſh Hearts have cauſed them to err; but now is the Day ſprung from on high even the mighty Day of the Lord, therfore the night muſt vaniſh away; for the Darkneſs cannot ſtand before the Brightneſs of his Coming, nor before the Gloriouſneſs of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, therefore it is time for the Prince of Darkneſs to ariſe &amp; to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together the uttermoſt of his Strength; for now is his Kingdom
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:48769:64"/>
invaded on every Side, even by the Lamb and his Followers, who is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to make War in Righteouſneſs, and by patient ſuffering ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his Kingdom, and bruiſe the Serpent's Head. Now thou that readeſt, haſt thou not heard of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who dare not ſwear, nor dare not tell a Lye, who cannot ſtoop nor bow their Knees, nor put off their Hats in Honour to any man's Perſon in the World, and which cannot give any vain flattering Titles to man, neither can have any Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with workers of Iniquity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they enter into any exceſs of Riot with them, neither dare they ſpeak any other Language then that which the Saints in former Ages ſpoke, and ſtand as Witneſſes againſt all vain Talks and fooliſh Jeſting, and cannot reſpect the Perſon of any man becauſe therein they ſhould commit Sin; who dare not to do unto any man, but as they would be done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:48769:64"/>
in the like Condition; who bears their Teſtimony againſt all the vain Worſhips of the World, and all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Profeſſors, who profeſs God in Words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but deny him in their Lives and Converſations? and haſt thou not at ſometimes heard their very Enemies ſay, that they believed that many of them were honeſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that their dealing towards them hath been honeſt and juſt? and haſt thou not heard, that ſome of them have wiſhed, that they could live as thoſe People do? and haſt thou not heard the People of the World report, of what undaunted Spirits thoſe People are, who fear not the Frowns, nor the lofty looks of the greateſt Potent upon the Face of the Earth? and on the other ſide, haſt thou not heard the rude People of the World, (even Drunkards, Swearers, Lyars and Covetous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſuch as live in all manner of Exceſs of Riot) cry out, that theſe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:48769:65"/>
are Deceivers, Deluders and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, and that they are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to live upon the face of the Earth; and haſt thou not heard what petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning to the Powers of the Earth there hath been againſt them, and what ſtocking, ſtoning, knocking down in their publick Aſſemblies, haling before Magiſtrates, whipping and ſending to the Bridewels, and what long Impriſonments have been ſuffered by many, and by ſome (even to the Death) who have thereunto been committed by the power of the Earth? and haſt thou not heard of what thoſe People have ſuffered in <hi>New-England,</hi> by the great red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, who is riſen in thoſe People, who once fled out of <hi>Old-England,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Fear of that which they now exerciſe in a far greater meaſure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe whom the Lord hath ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, to declare (the Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his mighty Day) unto them, who in their time in <hi>Old-England</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:48769:65"/>
ſhould have born their Teſtimony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhops, Prelates, and Prieſts, and have ſtood in the Croſs to that (in their own Walls) which cauſed them to flee from the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſo from the Croſs which ſhould have crucified that Nature, which they carried with them out of <hi>Old-England,</hi> even that which is now riſen in them, which cauſes them to exerciſe ſuch grievous Tortures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bodies of thoſe whom the Lord hath ſent amongſt them, even impriſoning and whipping, caſting into Dungeons and naſty Holes, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Ropes, until their Fleſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as Gelly, whereby they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſuch a hardneſs of Heart, that they have exceeded all Nations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun in Tyranny, the very <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves have ſtood more in the Fear and Dread of the Lord then they; for they continually thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Blood, who after they have cut off the Ears of the Lord's People,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:48769:66"/>
which no Nation under the Heavens (except themſelves) did dare to do, yet they not thinking that ſufficient, have ſince drunk two more larger Draughts then (then ever yet was drunk by any in this our Age) of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood, whoſe Righteous Lives will ſtand as a Brand of Infamy upon them and their Generation to all Eternity, and when the Lord makes Inquiſition for Blood that will not be forgotten. Now haſt thou heard that at any time, theſe People ever plotted or contrived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way or means whereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves by the Arm of fleſh, or that they have riſen, or were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by the Powers of the Earth at any time? but at all times the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers of the Earth ſtood againſt them and oppoſed them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet doſt thou not ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that theſe People have dayly encreaſed, and how many are dayly gathered unto them, and how they dayly learn to bear the Reproaches
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:48769:66"/>
of <hi>Moab,</hi> and the Revilings of the Children of <hi>Ammon.</hi> and are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to bear and ſuffer all with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſo that in their ſuffering they may glorifie God, and therein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more then Conquerers by the Power of Chriſt, who is riſen in them, and is become the Captain of their Salvation? Now, whoever thou art that readeſt conſider ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in thy own Heart; for here thou ſeeſt the Diviſion that is made between them that fear the Lord, &amp; them that fear him not, if thou canſt with a ſingle Eye behold it; but if thou ſtandſt in doubt, as yet, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this thing, come but into a true Examination in thy own Heart and Conſcience; for aſſuredly there is ſomething in the Matter, therefore what thinkeſt thou? doſt thou think that it is for nought, that theſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forſake their Goods and Lands, their Wives and Children, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, as it were ſtrangers, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:48769:67"/>
their Country and to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Houſe; and to travail from Country to Country, through Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and Sufferings, through Mockings and Reproaches, through Hunger and Cold, and ſo come to be counted as Vagabonds and Wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, having no Habitation in the Earth, that they might have a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation in God? for <hi>Cain</hi> he was a Vagabond, although he builded a City, and called it by his Son's Name, yet he had no Habitation in God, therefore was he a Vagabond; but theſe who have a Habitation in God, they are no Vagabonds, but have ſought, &amp; have found the City whoſe Builder is God, and they are willing and contented to part with all, ſo that they may have a Habitation in that City.</p>
               <p>But now herein ſtands the clear Truth of the Difference, the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time is now come, and drawing near, even at the very Door wherein
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:48769:67"/>
the Lord God is riſen and ariſing to fulfil his Promiſe, which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed unto <hi>Adam</hi> in the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> after his Fall, that is, <hi>That the Seed of the Woman ſhould bruiſe the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent's Head, and he ſhould bruiſe his Heel:</hi> And now is he come and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, who will cut <hi>Rahab,</hi> and wound the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and bruiſe to powder the very Head of the Deceit and the Iniquity, which have long lodged in the Hearts of the Sons and Daughters of Men. And now is the Stone, even the Stone which is elect and precious, which is to be laid in <hi>Sion,</hi> which is the chief Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-Stone, that the Builders have long refuſed, which Stone hath long lain buried in the Mountain of Sin and Tranſgreſſion; but now is the Stone cutting it ſelf out of the Mountain, which ſhall ſmite at the Feet of the Image, even at the very Ground and Foundation of Iniquity; and this Stone will become a Mountain,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:48769:68"/>
which ſhall cover the whole Earth, which the Mountain of the Houſe of the Lord, which is to be eſtabliſhed atop of all Mountains and above the Hills, and the Nations ſhall flow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it. Therefore ſeeing the Treader upon the Serpent's Head is come, and hath made himſelf manifeſt in many, therefore hath Pangs taken hold on many of them in whom the ſeed of the Serpent bears rule, ſo that that Seed ſtrives and ſtruggles in them, even as a Dying Man, on whom the Pangs of Death had taken hold; and this is the Cauſe that them in whom the ſeed of the Serpent ſtill rules in power, are ſo bitter and invitered againſt the Seed of the Woman, in whom its raiſed: but yet, though they raiſe up the uttermoſt of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and gather together <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog,</hi> and come up even the whole breadth of the Earth to encompaſs the Camp of the Saints about, yet they ſhall not proſper; for this <hi>John</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:48769:68"/>
ſaw in his <hi>Revelation,</hi> and he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaw a Fire come out of Heaven, and devoured them; therefore do I in tender Love to thee adviſe thee to conſider of theſe things, and lay them to Heart; for this is the Day of thy Viſitation, therefore trifle it not away for meer Vanity &amp; things of nought; for it paſſes away from thee faſter then thou art aware of; for this is the Time which the Lord hath given thee to make thy Calling and Election ſure: Therefore be not like fooliſh <hi>Eſau,</hi> ſell not thy Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a Meſs of Pottage, for if thou doſt, thou wilt hereafter come to ſeek it (perhaps) with Tears, when thou mayeſt not attain it; therefore while the Lord is yet ſo tender towards thee, who ſtandeth with his Arm of Mercy ſpread o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, ready to receive thee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tarry not, but ariſe and come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; for the Winter is near ſpent, and the Summer draweth on, the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:48769:69"/>
Fig-tree hath put forth her Bud, and the Vine her tender Grape, &amp; the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Birds and the Voice of the Turtle is heard in our Land; and now after all this Dark Night of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy is the Glorious Day dawned and dawning unto many, which many precious Souls have longed and breathed after, deſiring that they might have ſeen it, but they could not attain thereunto, but by Faith; therefore conſider what Age and Generation thou art fallen in, even in a Day that is neither dark nor light, but as the Evening-tide, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Son of Man is come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, therefore trim up thy Lamp, and provide Oyl in thy Veſſels; for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely, the Bridegroom is coming, and the Voice of them who rejoyce and ſing <hi>Halelujah</hi> thereat is heard, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prepare and come away, left thou be ſhut out of the Bride-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſo remain in Eternal Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, even with the Prince thereof, &amp;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:48769:69"/>
his Legions, who is bound up in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Chains of Darkneſs, never more to come into the Light; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is the Word of the Lord God unto thee, whoever thou art, Rich or Poor, High or Low, <hi>If thou ſleight this the Day of thy Viſitation, which the Lord (out of his tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) hath freely given to thee, the time will come that thou wilt ſee theſe things to be an Everlaſting Truth, then thou wilt ſee how thou haſt ſpent thy precious Time in Vanity.</hi> Therefore come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Light; come unto that which makes manifeſt Iniquity in thy own Heart, for that is the Light, and obey it, that thou mayeſt find Eternal Peace and Reſt to thy Soul.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. M.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:48769:70"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>A Word of Love unto the Sons and Daughters of</hi> Zion, <hi>and a Hand held forth unto them who are yet in</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt's <hi>Captivity, and to them who are yet in the Deſert Wilderneſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>My dear Friends, you whom the Lord hath gathered and is gathering into the Choſen Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and into the Royal Prieſthood; and you whoſe Garments are waſhed in the Blood of the Lamb, which hath been ſlain from the Foundation of the World, which Lamb of God you can behold and witneſs, that he is come, and hath taken and is taking away the Sins of many, who have formerly lived in the World, but now they are come to be choſen out of the World, and are many of them become a peculiar People unto the Lord; therefore you dear Sons and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:48769:70"/>
Danghters of <hi>Zion,</hi> ariſe let your Light ſhine forth into the dark World, that you may be faithful Witneſſes, that <hi>Zion</hi>'s Redeemer is come, and is redeeming <hi>Zion</hi> through Judgments, &amp; her Converts through Righteouſneſs, that ſo they who turn Judgments into Wormwood, and Righteouſneſs into Hemlock, may come to ſee the Gloriouſneſs of <hi>Zion</hi>'s Light to ſhine forth through you, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Shame may come to cover their Faces, and the Dread and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment of the Lord may take hold of them; for aſſuredly Friends, this I know, that as you ſtand in the pure Light, and in Obedience to the Meaſure of God made manifeſt in you, your Words and Actions being all ſpoken and acted therein, will reach to the Witneſs of God in all Hearts, and in all Conſciences; and ſo, as you ſtand faithful to the Lord, he will make you a Dread &amp; a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to your Enemies, let them be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:48769:71"/>
ſo many; and you will triumph over them all in the Lord; yea, the Devils ſhall bend and bow before you<hi>:</hi> Neither ſhall the Gates of Hell or Death prevail againſt you; for you are of the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which are numberleſs, to whom the Lord hath ſent a Deliverer to redeem you out of your Captivity, even out of ſpiritual <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Houſe of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; therefore dear Friends be wiſe, and walk circumſpectly, and let the Tenderneſs of your Love flow forth freely one to another; for the Lord your Redeemer is Love, and thoſe that follow him are begotten into Love, therefore Chriſt Jeſus the Captain of our Salvation, gave a remarkable Sign whereby all men might know that you are his Diſciples, which was, <hi>Your Love one towards another;</hi> therefore let your Moderation and Love appear to all men, that ſo they may be convinced in their own Conſciences, that the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:48769:71"/>
Lord is at hand; for verily Friends, there is yet a mighty Seed which is under the Hand of hard hearted <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach,</hi> who will not let <hi>Iſrael</hi> go free to worſhip the Lord his God; but the Lord is raiſing up his Prophet like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> who ſhall bring Plagues and Vengeance upon ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> even that corrupt Nature, which lodgeth in the Hearts of the Sons and Daughters of Men, which oppreſſeth the Seed of God, which Seed groans under the burden of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, unto whoſe ſighs and groans the Ears of the Lord God of Hoſts are opened, &amp; he will redeem it all in his own appointed time, therefore Dear Friends, as the Lord hath ſpared us in our Tranſgreſſions, and in our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, even for his own Seed Sake, that his Mercies might be made known by us unto the World; let us now wait with Patience until the Lord hath finiſhed his own work, who will redeem his own Seed in his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:48769:72"/>
time, that ſo we may all ſit down in his everlaſting Land of Reſt when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his <hi>Egyptian</hi> hoſt ſhall be deſtroyed, even in the red Sea of his Wrath, therefore thou ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of <hi>Zion</hi> ariſe, and ſhew thy ſelf forth in thy Beauty, that ſo Fear and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may take hold on all thine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: And you Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Zion,</hi> come forth and appear in your Might; for before your Faces all Fleſh is as Graſs, and all the Glory of man is but as the Flower of the Field; for the Appearance of your Beauty is admirable; for it ſtains the Beauty of all Fleſh, and marrs the Glory of all the Sons and Daughters of Men; therefore ariſe and threſh the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, even to Duſt, and let the Hills be laid low before you, and raiſe up the Valeys, that ſo a plain Way may be made for the Lord and for his ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomed ones to paſs over: Go on my dear Friends, go on in the Dread and in the Authority of the Lord, cut
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:48769:72"/>
down, and ſpare not, neither let your Eye pity, that the Nations may know, that the Sword of the Lord God is drawn forth and furbiſhed to cut down, and to deſtroy that Nature in all the Sons and Daughters of Men, which have rebelled againſt him, whereby his pure Seed hath been kept in Bondage<hi>:</hi> And you my dear Friends, who are yet but paſſing out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and you, who are got into the Wilderneſs, beware that you look not back into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that you hanker not after the Fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots thereof, even the Glory of this vain World; but go on boldly, and with Cheerfulneſs, &amp; let your Eye be alwayes, &amp; at all times fixed on him, who firſt brought you out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> even from out of your former groſs Lives and Converſation; and follow him in Truth and in Faithfulneſs, &amp; he will bring you through the deſert Wilderneſs, even by a mighty hand, and by his Arm of Strength, which
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:48769:73"/>
he now has ſtretcht forth unto you; which Arm he is making bare, even in the Sight of the Nations, therefore go on and be valiant for Truth, and lift up the weak Hands, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the feeble Knees; for now is he making himſelf known, who will aſſemble her that halted, and gather her that was ſcattered, and bring back again that which was driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; even he that binds up the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted is come and coming, who will ſatisfie the Thirſty Soul, and ſpeak comfortably unto all them that truly breath after the Eternal Peace and Welfare of <hi>Zion,</hi> and the Redemption of the oppreſſed Seed, which hath long breathed after Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; therefore wait in the Patience in the Stilneſs and in the Coolneſs of your Spirits, that you may come to feel that to ariſe daily in you, which will daſh down all Incumbrances, who rebukes the Winds, and ſtills the raging Seas at his Command,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:48769:73"/>
who is the only begotten of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who begets all his Children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Love; for God is Love, and that which is begot of him in all Hearts, is Love and Tenderneſs unto all men, but eſpecially one towards another<hi>:</hi> Therefore dear Friends beware of that Spirit, which would ariſe in you to cauſe evil Surmiſings one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or that would open an evil Eye to look forth at one anothers Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of that Spirit that would cauſe any ſecret Rejoycing thereat, though it be never ſo hidden; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and bring it to the Bar of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before it gets any Head or Strength in you, that ſo it may be condemned before it go any further: And beware of that Spirit that ſhall ariſe to cauſe a Deadneſs or a Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in you, as to the things of God, &amp; would carry you back to feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which you have formerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, and that would cauſe you to give way to a ſecret Envy, which
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:48769:74"/>
will be Ready to ariſe in you, againſt them who in honeſt Simplicity walk in the true Obedience to the Meaſure of God made manifeſt in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, when they feed in the Banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Houſe of their Father, you may, perhaps, find Barrenneſs and Empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the preſent; I ſay, beware of that Spirit; for it is he that cauſeth the Barrenneſs, and the want; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wait in that which diſcovers him, and makes him known; and come unto true Obedience thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and you ſhall ſee him, and all that would ariſe to oppoſe it ſelf againſt the pure ſeed of God in you, caſt into utter darkneſs, from whence it ariſes; for the Prince of Darkneſs with all his Legions, is not able to ſtand in the Preſence of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; of his Chriſt, who is the Light of the World, and hath enlightned you with a meaſure of himſelf, which if you faithfully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and follow, you will feel a living Zeal to ariſe in your Hearts for the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:48769:74"/>
Lord, and for his Truth, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, an utter Enmity againſt all the Deeds of Darkneſs, both in your ſelves, and likewiſe in all others; and you will feel that to ariſe in you, which truly breaths after the Good and Welfare of all the Sons &amp; Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of men; and you will come to ſuffer with the Seed of God, which is oppreſſed, both in your ſelves, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam;</hi> and bleſſed are all they that come to witneſs this in Truth and in Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and that are f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithful to that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thing, that makes this known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them; for verely they ſhall be made Rulers over much: Therefore dear Friends, you that are newly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten into the eternal Truth of God for your Sakes is this declared, by him, who hath by the good Hand of God been carried through theſe things, and hath ſeen much of the Strength and Subtilty of the Enemy, who like a roaring Lyon goes about,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:48769:75"/>
ſeeking whom he may devour, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtand in the Light, and in the Croſs, even that which croſſeth the carnal Mind, and in that there is Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer againſt all his Aſſaults, and wait in Stilneſs at all times, that ſo you may come to hear the Voice of the Lord, and to obey and follow it; for Obedience is better then Sacrifice, and that is it, which the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of you, and without that you ſhall not eat of the good of the land, even the promiſed land of Reſt and Peace, which the Lord is now bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his People into, where they ſhall feed in fat Paſtures, even by the Springs of living Water, under the Shadow of the Tree of Life, whoſe Fruit is pleaſant to the Taſte, and whoſe Leaves are for the Healing of the Nations; in which Land is Peace and Pleaſantneſs, and Joy and Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, where the redeemed of the Lord walk, and lie down in Reſt and perfect Peace; where no
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:48769:75"/>
vultrous Eye can come, and where the Devourer cannot enter; where the Abominations, which make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, cannot ſtand: The Gates of which land have long been the gates of the Enemy; but now is the time appointed come, &amp; the true ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> is riſen in many, and doth poſſeſs the Gates of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and many are they that are entred in through the Gates to this Land of Reſt and Redemption, Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the Lord God forever, and for evermore: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny are they, that are yet entring, and to enter; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be couragious and faint not; for the Promiſe is unto all, in whom tho Seed is in any meaſure made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, which Seed ſhall poſſeſs the gates of his Enemies; and though the Enemy hath long ſtood in the Gate, and ſtopped the paſſage, and though it may yet ſtop, in many, the paſſage through which the Seed ſhould come forth out of Bondage,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:48769:76"/>
&amp; Oppreſſion, yet mind not the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but mind him who has promiſed &amp; will perform, even that the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhall poſſeſs the Gates of its Enemies, which Seed is Chriſt in the Male, and in the Female. I ſay, mind not that which brings in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, but mind that which lets you ſee them, and ſtills and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets all again<hi>:</hi> For Friends, the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail which is to be fought in every one of you, is hard, and the Enemy is ſtrong and mighty, therefore come forth, even forth of the Polutions, to the Help of the Lord againſt the mighty; for <hi>Curſed is he, that comes not forth to the Help of the Lord againſt the mighty;</hi> therefore ſtand forth with your loyns girded about with Truth, and put on the Breaſt plate of Faith and the Helmet of Salvation; for a mighty work hath the Lord God to do in the Earth, Inſtruments, in whoſe Hand, many of you may be, if you are willing and obedient, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:48769:76"/>
can with content take up the Croſs dayly, which croſſeth the carnal, and deſpiſe the Shame, then ſhall you be partakers of the Joy which is ſet before you, which Joy daſhes all the Glory of the World, and makes it appear as a thing of nought, for the Sake of which Joy many dear hearts have deſpiſed the Shame and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World, and have wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly undergone many grievous Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and have undauntedly tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over Death and Hell, even, to the Amazement of all their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; therefore bleſſed and happy are all you, that are called forth to ſuffer for the Name of the Lord, and of his Truth, in which Truth is Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower, to which you may fly in time of Diſtreſs, and you are ſafe from the Enemy, and from all his Strength &amp; Oppoſitions; and though he may exerciſe his Tyranny upon your outward man, yet that is a thing
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:48769:77"/>
of ſmall value; for that muſt to its Duſt again, from whence it came, yet that it cannot touch, without the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſion of him who is the Keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who never ſlumbers nor ſleeps: But you have a Life which is hid with God in Chriſt, which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, when all mortal things ſhall turn to the Duſt its Mother; which Life cannot be touched nor injured by no invitred Heart nor cruel Hand; therefore fear not man, nor the Sons of men; nay, I know you that are come into the true Fear of the Lord, you cannot fear man; for <hi>Fearfulneſs that ſhall ſurprize the Hypocrite, and Aſtoniſhment the double-hearted, when they that fear the Lord ſhall be as bold as Lyons:</hi> Therefore if Sufferings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto thee my dear Friend, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art that readeſt, they will be as precious Jewels unto thee, and thou wilt come to be as Gold, which is purified in the Fire; and as thy Sufferings do abound upon thy out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:48769:77"/>
Body, ſo likewiſe ſhall Peace, and Tranquility flow in upon thee, as Rivers of Living Water, whereby thy Soul will come to be refreſhed abundantly; yea, thou knoweſt, that Pen cannot expreſs, nor Tongue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Endleſs Joy and Felicity which at all times accompanies thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat are faithful. Words are too ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o declare it, yet nevertheleſs for the Sake of them that languiſh, and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger after the living Bread, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with all that are faithful are ſatisfied and fed abundantly; I ſay, for the Sake of him that is hungry &amp; not yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ully ſatisfied is this written, that he may go on and not faint in his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail; for bleſſed art thou that hungers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd thirſts after Righteouſneſs; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f thou wilt wait and abide in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience, thou ſhalt be ſatisfied; for in our Father's Houſe is Bread enough, where all his Children are fed at his Table, in the Banqueting-Houſe of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48769:78"/>
Peace, therefore wait and be ſtill, and commune with thy Heart, and go not forth to look that abroad, which cannot be found any where, but at home in thy own Heart; and though at preſent thou mayſt ſee a Day of Diſtreſs, and a Night of Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, wherein Judgment may come to be laid to the Line, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Plummet, yet ſtand ſtill, &amp; wait on the Lord and in the Way of his Judgments, ſo ſhalt thou witneſs <hi>Zion,</hi> even the Seed of God within thee, to come to be redeemed through it, and <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ylon</hi> with all her Brats come to be thrown down, and daſhed in pieces by it; for now he that daſheth in Pieces is come upon our Walls, and entred into our Borders, even the Lord, who is now riſen to enter into Judgment with all Fleſh, and to purifie and to clenſe the Sons and Daughters of Men from all their Polutions, and to let them ſee the Filth of the Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:48769:78"/>
of <hi>Babylon</hi>'s Whore, which hath long reigned in the Hearts of the Children of Men, and hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Creation to groan under her Oppreſſion; now is the Lord riſen to rent her Covering, and to lay open her ſhame and Nakedneſs, that all that are not wilfully blind may ſee the Filth of her Polutions, and come out from her, leſt they be Partakers of her Plagues, which ſhall ſuddenly come upon her, that ſo the Lord may clenſe them, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie them, and make them fit Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for himſelf to dwell in; for that is the Work which the Lord is going to perform, and his mighty Arm ſhall bring it to paſs; for he will work, and who ſhall hinder it? and he will daſh all the Pot-ſherds to pieces that oppoſe themſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; for, who art thou that ſetteſt Bryars and Thorns in Battle againſt me? <hi>ſaith the Lord;</hi> Shall not I paſs through and burn them up?
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:48769:79"/>
Yea verely, Friend, this have our Eyes ſeen, and our Ears have heard, how the Lord hath torn the Powers of the Earth in pieces, and hath brought all their Contrivances to nought, who have ſought after their own Glory, and not the Glory of Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have ſate at reſt and eaſe, and have not partaken of the Day of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Trouble, but have ſought their own Intereſt, and not the Intereſt of the Lord, nor the Liberty of his People, but have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Innocent to lie under the Hands of grievous Oppreſſors, even the greedy Hirelings and the dumb Idol Shepherds, who have long made &amp; Prey upon the Lord's Heritage, and have ſcattered the Lord's Flock in the dark and cloudy Day, and cauſed them to wander upon the Barren Mountains<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have long fed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Fat, and clothed themſelves with the Wool, and have ſate at Reſt and Eaſe, and have cryed
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:48769:79"/>
                  <hi>peace</hi> whilſt men could put into their Mouthes; but now, them that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feed them any longer, they even prepare War againſt them, whereby they become a Prey unto them; ſo that the whole Land groans under that Oppreſſion more then any other, and the Righteous ſuffer, and no man layeth it to Heart; and for this Cauſe hath the Lord rebuked ſtrong Nations, and he will ſtill rebuke all them that ſhall ſet themſelves againſt him and againſt his People.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear Friends, wait ſtill on the Lord, who is the Strength of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the Redeemer of the Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who hath already for your ſakes, even for his Seed's ſake, which he hath raiſed in you, overthrown all that have exalted themſelves againſt him, and againſt his Anointed, even Kings, Princes, Protectors and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments: I ſay, the Lord hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown and daſhed them in pieces as Potters Veſſels, becauſe they relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:48769:80"/>
not the Oppreſſed, nor pleaded the Cauſe of the Innocent, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath ſwift Deſtruction overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them as an Armed Man, and there was none to deliver. And for your ſakes, O ye Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Sion,</hi> hath the Lord brought theſe things to paſs, that the Nations may know that his Dread and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is with you, and at all times is amongſt you; for by you will he make himſelf known unto this croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and perverſe Generation; and they ſhall confeſs, that God of a truth is in you and amongſt you: And though his Appearance unto Proud Fleſh is without Form or Comlineſs, yet you know him to be as a Lilly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Thorns, who is the Beloved of your Souls, and the faireſt among Ten Thouſand, who is declaring his ſtrange Acts &amp; his wonderful Works in you, that which hath been hidden from Ages and Generations paſt, he is now making known even in and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:48769:80"/>
through you, whom he hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſound forth his Mighty Day in the Ears of all Fleſh, that ſo all may awake out of the Duſt, and come to Judgment; for now is he riſen and ariſing in all Hearts, who ſits upon the Throne, from before whoſe Face both the Heavens and the Earth ſhall flee away, and their place ſhall be no more found<hi>:</hi> And this is he that has long been waited for by many a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart and longing Soul, but now is he come and coming, and behold his Reward is with him; therefore bleſſed are they that patiently wait for the Day of his Appearance, who will wipe away tears from all Faces, and Sorrow and Sighing ſhall be no more; then ſhall all Tyranny and Oppreſſion be deſtroyed, and then ſhall Peace be eſtabliſht in the Earth, and Love and Unity among Men; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thus ſhall it be when <hi>Sion</hi>'s King ſhall come to Reign in Glory; for then the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:48769:81"/>
which have long ruled the Nations, and deceived thoſe that have dwelt in the Earth, and compelled people to worſhip and bow down to their Abominations, and to receive the Mark of the Beaſt in their Right Hands or in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir Foreheads, even the Mark of Sin and Tranſgreſſion, that Monſtrous Beaſt, whoſe Mark hath long been upon the Nations, without which Mark no man hath bought or ſold for theſe many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and they that would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Mark came to be ſlain<hi>:</hi> But now, Praiſes be unto the Lord, he hath brought forth many who cannot worſhip Man's Proud Will, that Monſtrous Beaſt, neither can they receive his Mark any longer; for their Father's Name is written in their Foreheads, and they are come forth of great Tribulation, and their Garments are waſhed white in the Blood of the Lamb; and theſe follow the Lamb of God (who is now come
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:48769:81"/>
to take away the Sins of the World) whither ſoever he goeth, even Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Light of the World, who hath enlightned every one that is come into the World with a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his true Light.</p>
               <p>Therefore, dear Friends, you that are obedient to the Light, and own it to be your Rule and Guide, you are they whom the Lord hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to place his Name in, for whoſe ſakes the Lord is now riſen to plead with <hi>Egypt</hi>'s King, and all his Hoſt; and though they now harden their Hearts as an <hi>Adamant,</hi> and bend their Brows as Braſs, &amp; ſtiffen their Necks as an Iron Sinnew, yet will the Lord God bring them low, even unto the Duſt in this his great Day, wherein his Jealouſie is broken forth againſt all Fleſh, becauſe they have corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Wayes, and have not turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his Reproof; but have caſt his Judgments behind their Backs, and turned his Grace (that hath appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:48769:82"/>
unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m) into Wantonneſs, and trampled the Blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant under their Feet; but as it was in the dayes of old, ſo will it be now in this latter Generation, when Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity was at the height, and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion did moſt abound in <hi>Egypt</hi> upon the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who was the Fleſhly Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> then did the Lord ariſe (to plead their Cauſe) who brought Judgments and Plagues up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and deſtroyed <hi>Pharaoh, Egypt</hi>'s King, with all the Firſt-born, and all his Mighty Hoſt; ſo likewiſe <hi>Sodom,</hi> when Iniquities were at the very height, and their Sins did greatly abound, then did the Lord's Wrath ſuddenly break forth upon them, as ſoon as Juſt <hi>Lot</hi> was put forth from amongſt them, even in Flames of Fire from Heaven, and devoured them; ſo likewiſe, dear Friends, you that ſigh and cry for the Abominations that are done in the midſt of the Earth, let not your
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:48769:82"/>
Hearts faint; for behold, he that is clothed in Linnen fine and white, which is the Righteouſneſs of him that ſanctifieth, and of them that are ſanctified; for he that ſanctifieth, and them that are ſanctified, are all one; He is gone forth to ſeal and to ſet a Mark on all your Foreheads, that ſigh and that cry at the Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are committed by him that makes deſolate, that ſitteth where he ought not, and after he hath ſealed you all even unto Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, then ſhall them that have the charge over the Earth draw near, every one with his Slaughter Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in his Hand, and ſhall follow after him that has ſealed you, &amp; ſhall ſmite and ſhall not ſpare, neither ſhall their Eye take pity, but they ſhall utterly ſlay Old &amp; Young, both Maid &amp; little Children, and Women; but you, upon whom the Mark is, they ſhall not come near: him that readeth, let him underſtand; for the Lord is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:48769:83"/>
and he will ſmite the Earth with a great Slaughter, and all Fleſh ſhall know that he is the Lord, and that he ruleth over the Kingdoms of men, and he will utterly deſtroy that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that hath oppreſſed his pure Seed in you, and in all the Sons and Daughters of Men, and his own Seed ſhall come forth to ſerve him in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs; and though the Whore, the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet have long born rule over the Heritage of the Lord, yet now is the time drawing near, when they ſhall be taken and bound, and caſt into the Lake which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them, even for that Nature which would not have the Lord nor his Chriſt to reign over them; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that may all the Enemies of the Lord be juſtly included; and that is it which ruleth in the rebellious Sons and Daughters of Men, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth them forth into Pride, Envy and High-mindedneſs one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:48769:83"/>
and into Diſobedience to the Lord and his pure Commands; and this is it which the Lord is riſen to deſtroy, and not the Creatures; for <hi>Chriſt came not to deſtroy Men's Lives, but to ſave them;</hi> therefore where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou readeſt any thing of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, it is not meant the Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Creature, or of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Life, but the Deſtruction of that Life in the Creature which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belleth againſt the Lord, which Life may truly be called Death; for if that be followed by the Creature, it will be the Death of the Immortal Soul; and this is him which the Lord is riſen to deſtroy, and not the Creatures; therefore ſaith Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>O Death, I will be thy Death; O Grave, I will be thy Deſtruction.</hi> So Friends, this is the Enemy, that you are to wait with Patience to ſee it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in your own Particulars firſt, and then aftewards that you may ſee it deſtroyed in others in the general;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:48769:84"/>
and bleſſed &amp; happy are all you who have witneſſed the Dead raiſed, which hath long lain in the Grave, under the Chains of Death, and can now truly witneſs your Part in the firſt Reſurrection, and that you are truly riſen with Chriſt, the Seed; for, over you the ſecond Death ſhall have no Power.</p>
               <p>And you, Friends, that are as yet brought but in part to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things, be ſtill and quiet in your Minds, and beware of feeding upon Knowledge which is out of the Life; for Knowledge will puff up, but it is Grace that edifies; therefore wait in the pure Patience, that you may feel the Life to ſtir in you; for that is the True Bread that comes down from Heaven, which Bread is the Soul's Food; for the Soul cannot be ſatisfied with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for, to Know the Truth and the Things of God, and not to live in them, therein ſtandeth the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:48769:84"/>
Therefore, dear Friends, to whoſe Hands this may come, wait that you may feel the Life, which will bring forth the Travails of your Souls, and then Knowledge will be encreaſed, and Truth will abound, and Eternal Peace and Happineſs will attend you whereſoever you go, and the Dread and Authority of the Lord will be with you at all Times &amp; Seaſons, &amp; as it has been a Dread and a Terror to that Nature in you which rebelled againſt the Lord whilſt you were in the Polutions, ſo likewiſe if you are faithful the Lord will make you a Dread and a Terror to all Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers whereſoever you come, &amp; they will be afraid of your Faces and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to traſngreſs againſt the Lord in your hearing; and theſe things I know that many Thouſands can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be Truth, and all that are faithful ſhall witneſs the ſame, and ſee it accompliſhed in the Lord's due time; unto whom be Eternal Praiſes
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:48769:85"/>
and Dominion given by all that fear him, for that he has brought this his wonderful Work to paſs, and hath revealed his Secrets even to Babes, and to ſuch as fear his Name.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given forth</dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>by one which hath long mourned in</hi> Sion, <hi>and is a Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with the Seed, who waiteth for the Redemption of all Creatures from under the Band of Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they may all be brought unto the Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God, known to many by the Name of</hi> Richard Moore.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48769:85"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
